<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Eli Bendersky's website - Blogging</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/feeds/blogging.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://eli.thegreenplace.net/</id><updated>2023-05-09T03:06:22-07:00</updated><entry><title>Twenty years of blogging</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/twenty-years-of-blogging/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-08T20:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-09T03:06:22-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2023-05-08:/2023/twenty-years-of-blogging/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog has now been running for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/06/why-start-a-weblog"&gt;20 years!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty years... a significant chunk of a human's adult life; while so
many things in my life have changed since May 2003, the blog has remained a
constant companion. This milestone inspired me to do some archaeology using the
amazing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://archive.org/web/"&gt;Wayback …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog has now been running for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/06/why-start-a-weblog"&gt;20 years!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty years... a significant chunk of a human's adult life; while so
many things in my life have changed since May 2003, the blog has remained a
constant companion. This milestone inspired me to do some archaeology using the
amazing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://archive.org/web/"&gt;Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt;. It didn't have the very
first post, but I dug up one from just a week or so later - &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/13/book-review-the-designers-guide-to-vhdl-by-p-ashenden"&gt;a book review&lt;/a&gt;.
Here's how it looked on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://use.perl.org/~spur/journal/"&gt;http://use.perl.org/~spur/journal/&lt;/a&gt; (this link is long
dead, of course) in May 2003:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="How this blog looked twenty years ago" class="align-center" src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2023/blog-twenty-years-ago.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I wrote an update at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/05/06/ten-years-of-blogging"&gt;10 year mark&lt;/a&gt;, the blog
looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="How this blog looked ten years ago" class="align-center" src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2023/blog-ten-years-ago.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The looks - along with the hosting and the software used to generate and run the
blog - changed in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/blogging-setup-with-pelican/"&gt;September 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and the
blog has had roughly the current format ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've made some adjustments to the infrastructure - comments outgrew their
usefulness and were &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2018/turning-off-blog-comments/"&gt;turned off in 2018&lt;/a&gt;.
To further reduce dependencies on
third-party services and make the blog faster and more self-contained,
blog analytics were switched to use a lightweight self-hosted solution &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/using-goatcounter-for-blog-analytics/"&gt;earlier
this year&lt;/a&gt;.
Some infrastructure changes and upgrades have been happening once in a while,
but these are completely transparent for readers. Otherwise, it's been going
pretty steady.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Downtime has been exceedingly rare, and the blog's serving of static HTML
proved to be robust and resilient to spikes - including &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; HN storms and
&amp;quot;hug of death&amp;quot; attempts. This is a great improvement from the previous
Wordpress-on-BlueHost approach, which struggled with uptime, especially in times
of load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blog has been averaging ~25 posts per year in the past 10 years, with
something like 100,000 monthly visits. The content has shifted with
my interests, from a focus on C++ and Python to more Go content with a mix of
Rust and other new technologies like WebAssembly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As before, big thanks to all my dedicated readers. Reader feedback has always
been a highlight of the blogging experience. I have no intention of stopping,
but can this blog &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; reach its 30th birthday? Only the future will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Using GoatCounter for blog analytics</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/using-goatcounter-for-blog-analytics/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-02-25T15:32:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-25T23:32:21-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2023-02-25:/2023/using-goatcounter-for-blog-analytics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever since I switched this website &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/blogging-setup-with-pelican/"&gt;to a static setup&lt;/a&gt; in 2014,
I've been trying to simplify it even more. In 2018 I turned off
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2018/turning-off-blog-comments/"&gt;Disqus comments&lt;/a&gt;,
eliminating a large source of latency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, an additional effort to reduce dependencies and be more self-contained
led to the replacement of Google …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever since I switched this website &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/blogging-setup-with-pelican/"&gt;to a static setup&lt;/a&gt; in 2014,
I've been trying to simplify it even more. In 2018 I turned off
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2018/turning-off-blog-comments/"&gt;Disqus comments&lt;/a&gt;,
eliminating a large source of latency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, an additional effort to reduce dependencies and be more self-contained
led to the replacement of Google Analytics by a self-hosted OSS analytics
solution. This post describes how I set up &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/arp242/goatcounter"&gt;GoatCounter&lt;/a&gt; to know how many people visit my
website over time, which pages are the most popular, and where visitors come
from (referer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="choosing-goatcounter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choosing GoatCounter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking for an analytics solution, two categories of tools emerge pretty
quickly in the research:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log parsers: these don't require the user's browser to make any additional
requests to log the visit; rather, they parse the web server's logs in the
background.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active analytics tools that inject some custom JS into every page;
your browser runs this JS, which typically makes a parameterized request
to another server to log the visit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While log parsers have the attractive property of not requiring any additional
user interaction (they are &amp;quot;offline&amp;quot;, in a way), the requirement to muck with
my Apache server's logs extensively gave me pause. Since I'm interested in
historical logs often going back a year or more, it still requires some tool
running continually on my server, ingesting logs all the time and updating some
database. Overall, the process of setting this up didn't seem sufficiently
simple to me - but I may have well overlooked something. Suggestions are very
welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the multitude of analytics tools, GoatCounter stood out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very privacy oriented, collecting so little data that a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.goatcounter.com/help/gdpr"&gt;GDPR notice isn't even required&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Light-weight; the added JS file is only 8 KiB and the server is
fast: 99.9% of requests are answered within ~2ms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can be self-hosted, which both reduces the cost if I already run a
server and reduces dependencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/arp242/goatcounter"&gt;OSS and written in Go&lt;/a&gt;.
This is not just a stylistic preference; since Go builds static binaries,
the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;goatcounter&lt;/tt&gt; tool is trivial to download and run. Much easier
deployment than, say, tools written in PHP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="setting-up-goatcounter-for-my-website"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting up GoatCounter for my website&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My GoatCounter setup is self-hosted; the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;goatcounter&lt;/tt&gt; server runs on the
same VPS as my blog, and serves at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://stats.thegreenplace.net"&gt;https://stats.thegreenplace.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;thegreenplace.net&lt;/tt&gt; domain is served by Apache that listens on
ports 80 and 443 on the VPS, I needed to configure Apache to reverse-proxy
traffic for the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;stats&lt;/tt&gt; subdomain to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;goatcounter&lt;/tt&gt;. For a general
explanation of how to set up such proxying, see &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/reverse-proxying-a-sub-domain-via-apache/"&gt;this earlier blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by downloading a pre-built &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;goatcounter&lt;/tt&gt; executable from the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/arp242/goatcounter/releases"&gt;releases page&lt;/a&gt;, and then
unzipping it in some directory &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$GOATDIR&lt;/tt&gt;. Then ask it to create a new
SQLite DB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ ./goatcounter-v2.4.1-linux-amd64 db -createdb create site \
      -vhost=stats.thegreenplace.net -email=eliben@gmail.com
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$GOATDIR/db/goatcounter.sqlite3&lt;/tt&gt;. Next, run the server itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ ./goatcounter-v2.4.1-linux-amd64 serve \
      db sqlite3+$GOATDIR/db/goatcounter.sqlite3 \
      -listen 127.0.0.1:5000 -tls http
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;goatcounter&lt;/tt&gt; server listens on local port 5000, which is not exposed
outside the VPS. Following the instructions of the aforementioned blog post,
Apache can then be set up to forward traffic for the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;stats&lt;/tt&gt; subdomain to this
port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all works well, the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;stats&lt;/tt&gt; subdomain should be accessible now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="restarts-and-automatic-backups"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Restarts and automatic backups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the VPS reboots, I don't want to restart the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;goatcounter&lt;/tt&gt; server manually.
Therefore, it has to be set up as a service, by adding a new systemd
configuration file at &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/etc/systemd/system/goatcounter.service&lt;/tt&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;# /etc/systemd/system/goatcounter.service
# Description of what the program does
[Unit]
Description=GoatCounter

[Service]
Type=simple
# If anything unexpected happens, Systemd will try to restart the program
Restart=always
# We need to send the absolute path of the database to GoatCounter.
ExecStart=$GOATDIR/goatcounter-v2.4.1-linux-amd64 serve -db sqlite3+$GOATDIR/db/goatcounter.sqlite3 -listen 127.0.0.1:5000 -tls http

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then the service can be started using &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;systemctl&lt;/tt&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sudo systemctl start goatcounter
$ sudo systemctl status goatcounter
● goatcounter.service - GoatCounter
     Loaded: loaded (/etc/systemd/system/goatcounter.service; enabled; vendor preset: enabled)
     Active: active (running) since Thu 2023-02-16 14:04:20 UTC; 1 week 1 day ago
   Main PID: 732 (goatcounter-v2.)
      Tasks: 16 (limit: 2324)
     Memory: 135.9M
        CPU: 15min 156ms
...
...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;systemctl&lt;/tt&gt; can be told to automatically run this service at startup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sudo systemctl enable goatcounter
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After clicking around the website for a bit, one will be able to observe that
GoatCounter's DB file is being updated. This is just a SQLite database, so it
can be explored using the command-line &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;sqlite3&lt;/tt&gt; tool; something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sqlite&amp;gt; select * from hits order by created_at desc limit 10;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure to back the DB up somewhere; I have a cron job that performs a
backup to cloud storage; this can be accomplished by first asking SQLite to dump
a backup file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sqlite3 goatcounter.sqlite3 &amp;quot;.backup $BKPFILE&amp;quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any custom filename as &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$BKPFILE&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="using-goatcounter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using GoatCounter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once GoatCounter is set up and running, it's pretty easy to use. Log into its
dashboard and poke around; the dashboard looks something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Screenshot showing a sample of how the GoatCounter dashboard looks" class="align-center" src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2023/goatcounter-screenshot.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clicking on &lt;em&gt;Help&lt;/em&gt; on the top right leads one to a nice documentation site with
lots of useful usage information. GoatCounter has &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; features; for example,
if you prefer working with the command-line, the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;goatcounter&lt;/tt&gt; binary (the
same one that acts as a server) has a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;dashboard&lt;/tt&gt; command that will render
a dashboard to the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A feature I like a lot is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.goatcounter.com/help/api"&gt;the API&lt;/a&gt;,
with a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.goatcounter.com/api2.html"&gt;detailed reference available&lt;/a&gt;.
This can be used to programmatically query your GoatCounter instance for all
kinds of aggregates and statistics. For example, to figure out which pages on
my website were the most popular during 2022, I can run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ curl -X GET &amp;#39;https://stats.thegreenplace.net/api/v0/stats/hits?start=2022-01-01&amp;amp;end=2022-12-31&amp;amp;daily=1&amp;#39; \
  -H &amp;#39;Content-Type: application/json&amp;#39; \
  -H &amp;#39;Authorization: Bearer &amp;lt;TOKEN-HERE&amp;gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(after generating an API token through the web dashboard).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dumps a JSON file with the data, which can be easily analyzed by a program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category></entry><entry><title>Turning off blog comments</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2018/turning-off-blog-comments/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-13T05:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T13:41:52-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2018-02-13:/2018/turning-off-blog-comments/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since switching to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/goodbye-wordpress-a-new-blog/"&gt;new statically-generated blog&lt;/a&gt;,
dealing with comments has been a continuous dilemma. On one hand, I wanted to
retain comments since it provides readers an immediate opportunity to respond,
suggest errors or additional material, etc. On the other hand, comments are - by
nature - dynamically generated, and it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since switching to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/goodbye-wordpress-a-new-blog/"&gt;new statically-generated blog&lt;/a&gt;,
dealing with comments has been a continuous dilemma. On one hand, I wanted to
retain comments since it provides readers an immediate opportunity to respond,
suggest errors or additional material, etc. On the other hand, comments are - by
nature - dynamically generated, and it felt bad adding heavy Disqus JS to my
otherwise static site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And indeed, over the years I've heard some complains that my blog is sluggish.
Wait, what? This makes little sense - I'm not on Wordpress any more; I simply
serve static HTML pages; oh wait, Disqus...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were other concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, whether comments are useful any more, at all. I've noticed that some of
my most popular posts generated hundreds of comments in Reddit and HN
discussions, but only a handful on the site. Why is that? I think the answer
is clear - folks who have Reddit and HN accounts have recognizable user names
there and any content helps their reputation. It's also a single place to
collect all your comments - on all blogs - rather than it being at the mercy of
the blog owner. I've also been receiving about a similar amount of comments by
plain email, and recently Twitter too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, Disqus has to pay the bills somehow, and I wasn't using their paid
package. It's not that it's very expensive, but paying as much for the comments
as I'm paying for the VM running this blog (along with some other things) just
feels wasteful. Moreover, since I've been resisting the idea of monetizing the
blog, something feels off about paying for multiple services just to run it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected, when you're not paying - you're the product. Disqus is injecting
ads in their comments section, and not ads of the good kind. Not stuff relevant
to my blog readers, but the terrible crap so common online recently - &amp;quot;man sheds
25 pounds by eating this fruit; doctors are shocked&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Oakland mom can't believe
her son's transformation&amp;quot; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been disabling these through Disqus's control panel, but after a while they
reappear - without any notification. I'm sure Disqus is acting within their TOS,
and I'm not blaming them, but this is no longer working for me. The energy spent
on tracking this would be better used by writing more blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I'll be disabling all comments on the blog. Instead, I'll provide a
direct link to my email and Twitter accounts. In addition, most of my posts get
to Reddit and HN fairly quickly and I usually try to follow the discussions that
ensue, so feel free to comment there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (2023-01-09):&lt;/strong&gt; I was reflecting on this change recently.
This has turned out to be a great decision I do not regret making.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category></entry><entry><title>Blogging setup with Pelican</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/blogging-setup-with-pelican/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-12T05:54:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2014-09-12:/2014/blogging-setup-with-pelican/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I launched the website redesign earlier this week, many people
asked me over email what kind of setup I'm using - blogging engine, hosting and
so on. Here's a short writeup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has changed for this website. First of all, I switched my hosting provider
from a shared Bluehost …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I launched the website redesign earlier this week, many people
asked me over email what kind of setup I'm using - blogging engine, hosting and
so on. Here's a short writeup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has changed for this website. First of all, I switched my hosting provider
from a shared Bluehost account (which I've had for the past 9 years or so) to a
VPS on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.digitalocean.com/"&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the blogging platform was changed from Wordpress to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/getpelican"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;. Pelican is a really nice and fast static-site
generator with a fairly clean Python codebase. It's easy to use and configure,
and the documentation is great; so overall I'd say I'm pretty happy with it. The
theme is my hacked up version of one of the existing bootstrap3-based themes.
One of the benefits of this is that the site is now much more usable on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for moving the existing content from the old Wordpress site, there are two
options. For smaller sites you may consider the auto-import capability Pelican
has for Wordpress imports. I didn't end up using it because I needed to preserve
the exact permalinks of my old website (there are &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of incoming links to
it out there, and it would be a shame to break them all), as well as
some other reasons. I just wrote a quick script that did my own importing from a
Wordpress XML dump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican lets older (back-ported) HTML content peacefully coexist with new,
ReST-authored content, which is very useful. For preserving the old permalinks,
it has the handy &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;save_as&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;url&lt;/tt&gt; attributes. Pelican also comes with
built-in integration to Google Analytics and Disqus, both of which took about 5
minutes to configure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I'm very happy with the transition. Static pages just make more
sense for a blog (even a fairly large one with over 1000 articles); the site now
feels incredibly fast to me. This is hardly surprising, given that it moved from
querying a DB and processing a bunch of PHP on a fairly congested machine to
just running a bare web server accessing the filesystem on a reasonably fast,
dedicated machine.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category></entry><entry><title>Goodbye Wordpress - a new blog</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/goodbye-wordpress-a-new-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-04T18:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2014-09-04:/2014/goodbye-wordpress-a-new-blog/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been unhappy with Wordpress for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/10/14/thinking-of-dumping-wordpress.html"&gt;quite some time&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, it's time to
move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll notice that the site looks different now. Hopefully you'll also notice
that it loads much faster, is more reliable and looks better on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please let me know if anything looks wrong or broken …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been unhappy with Wordpress for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/10/14/thinking-of-dumping-wordpress.html"&gt;quite some time&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, it's time to
move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll notice that the site looks different now. Hopefully you'll also notice
that it loads much faster, is more reliable and looks better on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please let me know if anything looks wrong or broken.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category></entry><entry><title>Website stats for 2013</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/01/11/website-stats-for-2013" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-11T05:54:56-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T13:41:52-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2014-01-11:/2014/01/11/website-stats-for-2013</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Two years ago &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/01/02/website-stats-for-2011/"&gt;I wrote a short summary&lt;/a&gt; of the visitor stats for this website during 2011. I skipped this in 2012, but here is a similar summary for 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: 2013 was the busiest year ever with 77K unique visitors per month on overage (compared to 66K in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Two years ago &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/01/02/website-stats-for-2011/"&gt;I wrote a short summary&lt;/a&gt; of the visitor stats for this website during 2011. I skipped this in 2012, but here is a similar summary for 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: 2013 was the busiest year ever with 77K unique visitors per month on overage (compared to 66K in 2012 and 56K in 2011).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="align-center" src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2014/01/stats20131.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monthly averages: 178,900 visits a month by 77,800 unique visitors, who viewed 628,400 pages. Once again the USA accounted for a large chunk of the traffic, with Germany, China and France lagging behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to search engines (mostly Google), most visitors came through Reddit, StackOverflow, and pygame.org. The most popular search keyphrases were &amp;quot;python multiprocessing&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;python destructor&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;book review of around the world in 80 days&amp;quot;, though these are fairly widely distributed (the highest occupies only 0.7% of the overall pie).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The five most viewed pages this year (counting only direct hits, not through the main page) were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/12/03/intel-i7-loop-performance-anomaly/"&gt;Intel i7 loop performance anomaly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2011/05/18/code-sample-socket-client-thread-in-python/"&gt;Code sample - socket client thread in Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/08/13/how-statically-linked-programs-run-on-linux/"&gt;How statically linked programs run on Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/01/05/understanding-your-own-code/"&gt;Understanding your own code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/01/16/python-parallelizing-cpu-bound-tasks-with-multiprocessing/"&gt;Python - parallelizing CPU-bound tasks with multiprocessing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, OS &amp;amp; browser distribution: 46% visitors were on Windows, with Linux lagging behind with 22%, followed by Mac with 18%. In browsers, Chrome is the big winner with 37%, followed by Firefox with 28%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks once again to all the dedicated readers of my blog :-)&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category></entry><entry><title>Ten years of blogging</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/05/06/ten-years-of-blogging" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-06T05:32:03-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T15:35:51-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2013-05-06:/2013/05/06/ten-years-of-blogging</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;It has occurred to me that the first post in this blog was &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/06/why-start-a-weblog/"&gt;10 years ago&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to dig up a bit of history. 10 years is a long time! As the post linked above shows, I even called it &amp;quot;weblog&amp;quot; then. The term &amp;quot;blog&amp;quot; seems to have …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;It has occurred to me that the first post in this blog was &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/06/why-start-a-weblog/"&gt;10 years ago&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to dig up a bit of history. 10 years is a long time! As the post linked above shows, I even called it &amp;quot;weblog&amp;quot; then. The term &amp;quot;blog&amp;quot; seems to have been coined in 1999, but probably wasn't popular enough in 2003 yet. That post also closes with a hope that the blog will last; it sure did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these 10 years the blog went from an obscure journal on use.perl.org that
only a few people knew about to 66,000 unique visitors with half a million page
views a month on average (stats for end-of 2012).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it looks very different from the initial &amp;quot;weblog&amp;quot;, it actually went through relatively few incarnations for its age. Starting &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/09/02/becoming-unhappy-with-useperlorg/"&gt;somewhere in 2005&lt;/a&gt; I became unhappy with use.perl.org and eventually &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/03/28/my-transition-to-blogger-is-complete/"&gt;moved the blog to Blogger&lt;/a&gt;. But Blogger itself was quite limited for serious programming-related blogging at the time, so it took me only two weeks to figure out it's not quite what I wanted and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/04/12/migrating-to-wordpress/"&gt;move to a Wordpress-based blog&lt;/a&gt; on my own domain and shared hosting (Bluehost). In the seven years that has passed since, the blog changed very little visually. I stretched the main viewing area bit by bit as high-resolution monitors became more common, installed a couple of minor plugins, but that's it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did change was the quality of content. As I &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/01/06/this-blog-and-google-division-of-responsibilities/"&gt;wrote here&lt;/a&gt;, the blog became much more technical with time, leaving the shorter and more personal posts to outlets like G+. The amount of technical content is also the reason the blog's popularity grew rapidly in the past few years. Apparently more people want to know how debuggers work and about the internals of Python and Linux loaders than about some random cool library I found or how I spent the last week at work being bored. Go figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dedicated readers will notice that the number of in-depth posts has slowed down in the past few months. This was to be expected, having moved to a different continent and started a much more demanding job. But I still hope to continue posting articles from time to time. This blog is far from being done! As for infrastructure, I was actually pondering to make a large change after yet another &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/10/14/thinking-of-dumping-wordpress/"&gt;break-your-site Wordpress upgrade&lt;/a&gt;. But I still haven't found time to do this. Maybe at some point I will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So thanks for reading, and wishing myself at least another 10 years of blogging. It has been an incredibly positive experience for me in many respects, and I have full intention of keeping it up as long as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Why I may not be able to help you</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/02/06/why-i-may-not-be-able-to-help-you" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-02-06T06:05:46-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2013-02-06:/2013/02/06/why-i-may-not-be-able-to-help-you</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
Since this blog features a lot of programming content, I'm receiving quite a bit
of email from people asking for help and advice, either about something specific
I wrote, or just general questions. This isn't new - it's been going on for
years. But my attitude towards this has changed over …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
Since this blog features a lot of programming content, I'm receiving quite a bit
of email from people asking for help and advice, either about something specific
I wrote, or just general questions. This isn't new - it's been going on for
years. But my attitude towards this has changed over time. Some years ago, I was
almost always willing to help. It was an opportunity to learn, and I was very
proud that someone I haven't ever met seeks my advice just because I
wrote a blog post about this and that. These days, however, it's getting harder
and harder for me to find the time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You have to realize that the amount of time I have for these things is extremely
small. I have a full-time job I find challenging and interesting, and most of my
off-work time is spent with my family. In the scant weekly hours I have
remaining for "hobby programming", I'm hopelessly oversubscribed with taking
care of my active open-source projects, contributing to Python and writing new
articles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This doesn't mean you should not ask. If the question pertains to a project I
actively maintain, I will certainly answer. The issue tracker for that project
is the best place to ask though, not email. If it's about something I wrote
relatively recently in the blog - there's also a high chance of getting an
answer. If it's something I wrote a while ago, it depends on how much I'm still
interested in the subject, so I may not be able to provide a good answer. In
some extreme cases I may not answer an email at all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The chance of a question getting a good answer also depends on the question. If
it's a short question asking about something very specific, and requiring a
short answer, it has a higher chance of getting a good answer. If you're dumping
a 50-page spec on me asking "how to design this" (this happened so many times it
doesn't even surprise me any longer), then not so much.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's also the issue of consulting. In general, I very rarely accept
consulting gigs. Historically, I've been mainly doing this to compensate for a
certain lack of challenge and passion in my day job, and this is no longer an
issue. However, you may try. I've been known to take some consulting gigs of
varying lengths if the subject interested me enough. Folks have also paid me
just to have long and meaningful email conversations about subjects they
believed I'm knowledgeable in. So if you need help with a work project and are
willing to pay, you may approach me with a consulting proposal, but please state
it explicitly. The amount I've been charging recently is $150 per hour, but a
new quote may depend on the nature of the project.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To conclude, while I'm certainly happy to be receiving such emails and often can
provide the answers, this is not guaranteed. If you only get a polite "I can't
help" from me, don't take it personally. I'm just a regular person with limited
free time who has to carefully allocate what it's being used for.
&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Personal"></category><category term="Programming"></category></entry><entry><title>This blog and Google+: division of responsibilities</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/01/06/this-blog-and-google-division-of-responsibilities" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-01-06T13:51:49-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T13:41:52-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2013-01-06:/2013/01/06/this-blog-and-google-division-of-responsibilities</id><summary type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Update (2020-11-14):&lt;/b&gt;Google+ has been discontinued a long time ago,
    and I've switched to using &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/elibendersky"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for quicker posts.
    &lt;/b&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This blog is certainly not a youngster, the first post in it being from May 2003 - almost 10 years ago. As I look in the earliest posts I'm filled with nostalgia …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Update (2020-11-14):&lt;/b&gt;Google+ has been discontinued a long time ago,
    and I've switched to using &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/elibendersky"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for quicker posts.
    &lt;/b&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This blog is certainly not a youngster, the first post in it being from May 2003 - almost 10 years ago. As I look in the earliest posts I'm filled with nostalgia - I was so different back then, but at the same time so alike. One interesting thing that immediately springs up is to completely different nature of my posts. Book reviews remained similar (although I started bundling most of them into quarterly summaries &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2010/07/08/summary-of-reading-may-june-2010/"&gt;some time ago&lt;/a&gt;), but the rest has changed. In the early years most of my posts were short. more personal and not too technical. Lately, most of my posts are quite technical, long, and non-personal.
    &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2011/07/29/ahoy-social-networking-google-account/"&gt;the last 1.5 years or so&lt;/a&gt;, I have an alternative outlet for the shorter, more personal posts - &lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/103282573189025907018/posts"&gt;my Google+ account&lt;/a&gt;. I'm pretty happy from what I get from G+, both for producing and consuming content. Producing is very easy from various kinds of devices, without arbitrary twitter-like restrictions, and it's reasonably easy to search my old posts (which is very important for me). Consuming is also quite nice because G+ turned out to be a popular outlet for people who share my interests, and many of the programmers I follow post updates on G+ from time to time.
    &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;So if you think I've become a robot producing technical articles, and want to see some more casual "&lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/103282573189025907018/posts/VncvVTvrBPc"&gt;hey I spilled coffee on my laptop&lt;/a&gt;" posts or random rants, check out &lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/103282573189025907018/posts"&gt;my Google+ page&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category></entry><entry><title>Thinking of dumping Wordpress</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/10/14/thinking-of-dumping-wordpress" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-14T15:16:42-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T13:41:52-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2012-10-14:/2012/10/14/thinking-of-dumping-wordpress</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
After the &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/08/19/wordpress-3-4-1-upgrade-screwed-up-my-blog-a-bit/"&gt;last
  upgrade of Wordpress&lt;/a&gt;, some minor aspects of my website are still broken. I
don't really have the energy any longer to fight WP, tinker with its godawful
PHP innards, and fix those problems after each major update.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

In other words, I'm nearing a conclusion to dump WP …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
After the &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/08/19/wordpress-3-4-1-upgrade-screwed-up-my-blog-a-bit/"&gt;last
  upgrade of Wordpress&lt;/a&gt;, some minor aspects of my website are still broken. I
don't really have the energy any longer to fight WP, tinker with its godawful
PHP innards, and fix those problems after each major update.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

In other words, I'm nearing a conclusion to dump WP altogether. Still don't know
what I'll do instead, but maybe rolling my own is the best solution in such a
case. It will give me ultimate control, as well as a fun project to hack on. To
avert the danger that this will be one of those eternal projects that will be
finished only after the Internet is replaced with something else, I will
continue blogging using the existing platform in the meantime. If you run into
some glitch with the website, please let me know.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

P.S. recommendations for a good hosting / platform to run Python 3 web apps
would be appreciated. 
&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category></entry></feed>