<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Eli Bendersky's website - Book reviews</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/feeds/book-reviews.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://eli.thegreenplace.net/</id><updated>2025-01-02T02:20:11-08:00</updated><entry><title>Summary of reading: October - December 2024</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2024/summary-of-reading-october-december-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-12-31T20:05:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-02T02:20:11-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2024-12-31:/2024/summary-of-reading-october-december-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Dr. Euler's Fabulous Formula&amp;quot; by Paul J. Nahin - a kind of sequel to the
previous book I read by this author (&amp;quot;An imaginary tale&amp;quot;). Here he collected
all the interesting mathematical explorations that didn't make the cut for
that book. I found this one to be much closer to a …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Dr. Euler's Fabulous Formula&amp;quot; by Paul J. Nahin - a kind of sequel to the
previous book I read by this author (&amp;quot;An imaginary tale&amp;quot;). Here he collected
all the interesting mathematical explorations that didn't make the cut for
that book. I found this one to be much closer to a textbook on the math
spectrum - most pages are crammed to the brim with integrals. Not easy
bedside reading, for sure, though it's still a good book and I appreciate
the author's enthusiasm about these topics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Sid Meier's Memoir!: A Life in Computer Games&amp;quot; by Sid Meier - an
autobiography by the famous computer game designer, best known for his
Civilization series. I think I was confused by what &amp;quot;designer&amp;quot; means in
Meier's case, because it turns out he's a coder extraordinaire who was
churning multiple solo-written games every year in the 1980s and into the
1990s. This book is very interesting and insightful; the author exudes
charming good nature, optimisim and some real hard-won design wisdom. A
delightful read for fans of the genre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Pnin&amp;quot; by Vladimir Nabokov - some notes on the life of a professor of Russian
who emigrated to the US around WWII and teaches at a fictional New England
college. The writing is masterful, but overall I felt like this novel's main
point eluded me - there's probably certain groups it was very relevant to, but
not me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Churchill - walking with destiny&amp;quot; by Andrew Roberts - a modern biography of
Winston Churchill, augmented with documents that only became available in the
last couple of decades. Even though this book is a behemoth (over 1000 pages
in the printed edition, 50 hours on audio), it's surprisingly readable
and engaging. The author does his best at being objective, providing detailed
accounts of criticism against Churchill and his failures. Nevertheless, the
character of the man emerging from this book is extremely impressive and
inspiring. I should probably try reading one of Churchill's own books - I
had no idea he was such a prolific and highly regarder author (with a Nobel
prize in literature).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Chip&amp;quot; by T.R. Reid - secondary title is &amp;quot;How two Americans invented
the microchip and launched a revolution&amp;quot;. Tells the story of the
simultaneous discovery of integrated circuits by Jack Kilby and Robert Noyce.
The first half of the book is fascinating; the second half is not as good and
mostly seems to be a filler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;How to rule the Universe, without alerting the orderlies&amp;quot; by Gregory
Khait - (read in Russian) yet another collection of short stories, with
some new stories on the interim period of immigration when people were
stuck in Europe while waiting for US visas. At least 1/3 of the stories
are repeats from previous books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;I Contain Multitudes: The Microbes Within Us and a Grander View of Life&amp;quot; by
Ed Yong - talks about the symbiosis of bacteria with multi-cellular
organisms, providing many examples of research findings from the animal and
kingdoms, including humans. The book is interesting, but this is a topic that
moves quickly, so the material gets outdated fast. Mostly, my impression was
surprise at how little we know about these things. The science here is
definitely in its infancy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The computational beauty of nature&amp;quot; by Gary William Flake - &amp;quot;computer
explorations of fractals, chaos, complex systems and adaptation&amp;quot;. A nice
book with some interesting code samples, but most of it feels awfully
outdated a quarter century after publishing. It's quite impressive that the
C code it bundles is still easy to compile and run, though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Math for English majors&amp;quot; by Ben Orlin - alas, by far Orlin's weakest work
IMHO. It's not clear what this book is even trying to do - a list of
humorous definitions for various mathematical terms? Drawing parallels
between elementary math and English grammar? I'll update this review if this
book becomes popular with my kids, but so far it seems unlikely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Guns of August: The Outbreak of World War I&amp;quot; by Barbara W. Tuchman - a
detailed history of the events leading to the outbreak of WWI and its first
month or so, in which Germany's attack into France was eventually blocked
and the Western front settled into the years-long trench warfare deadlock.
I found the first half of the book - dealing with the politics leading to
the war - the most insightful. It pairs wonderfully with one of my favorite
books - &amp;quot;All quiet on the Western front&amp;quot;, because it's a perfect contrast of
the decisions made in the upper eschelons vs. the reality on the ground for
millions of soldiers. The second half is more of a classical military history
of events, and I wasn't particularly impressed by it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Tom Swan and the Head of St George&amp;quot; by Christian Cameron - a wild adventure
story set in the late crusades era. A young English knight's escapades in
Italy, Greece and Turkey, full of unrealistic fighting, womanizing and
drinking. Occasionally fun, but mostly pretty silly. I don't think I'll be
reading the rest of the books in this series.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Poverty Safari: Understanding the Anger of Britain's Underclass&amp;quot; by Darren
McGarvey - a memoir of a Scottish rapper about growing up in a poor,
dysfunctional family in Glasgow in the 1990s, sharing his views of the
class-based social divides of society. The author's own struggles with
alcoholism and mental health issues play a major role in the book. Some parts
of this book are insightful, especially on the topic of class divides within
the liberal left.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;To Kill a Mockingbird&amp;quot; by Harper Lee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Anne of Green Gables&amp;quot; by L.M. Montgomery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Luzhin Defense&amp;quot; by Vladimir Nabokov&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Man's Search for Meaning&amp;quot; by Viktor Frankl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of reading: July - September 2024</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2024/summary-of-reading-july-september-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-30T17:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-01T01:40:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2024-09-30:/2024/summary-of-reading-july-september-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;A City on Mars&amp;quot; By Kelly and Zach Weinersmith - actual discussion of building
settlements on Mars occupies maybe 1% of this book. The authors have an
uncanny talent of focusing on all the least interesting aspects of space
exploration; whatever little is dedicated to science and engineering is
fairly shallow …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;A City on Mars&amp;quot; By Kelly and Zach Weinersmith - actual discussion of building
settlements on Mars occupies maybe 1% of this book. The authors have an
uncanny talent of focusing on all the least interesting aspects of space
exploration; whatever little is dedicated to science and engineering is
fairly shallow and reeks of techno-pessimism. That said, if the aspects of
space exploration that interest you most are politics, social structures,
legal frameworks, labor relations and mental health - go ahead and read this
book. Overall, I found it infuriatingly bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;What You Are Looking For Is in the Library&amp;quot; Michiko Aoyama - a sweet little
collection of loosely-related short stories. Just regular people living their
lives in Japan; the common theme is changing circumstances and how to deal
with them. I really enjoy books of this kind, and this one is very well done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Is this Wi-Fi Organic?: A guide to spotting misleading science online&amp;quot; by
Dave Farina - a valiant attempt to build up a solid scientific foundation
for debunking myths (focusing mostly on alternative medicine). Unfortunately,
the execution falls short. The tactic employed by the author is: explain
a bunch of science at a pretty shallow level, then present some claim to
debunk and then immediately jump to &amp;quot;this is clearly false, becasue science&amp;quot;.
Rinse; repeat. While entertaining, this isn't very convincing. From a book,
I'd expect much more. For example, Simon Singh's &amp;quot;Trick or Treatment&amp;quot; is much
better in this respect, because the debunking done with a lot of supporting
evidence, citing relevant research and studies. The good thing I can say
about this book is that I appreciate the techno-optimism and the science-first
approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;An imaginary tale&amp;quot; by Paul J. Nahin - tells the history of the discovery
and initial applications of the imaginary unit - &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;. Very interesting book
that fills an under-served niche between popular science and textbooks. The
book isn't easy to go through - it requires sophisticated math, at least at
the engineering undergrad level. Except the last chapter - which goes a
bit off the rails with complex analysis - this background should be sufficient
for the vast majority of the book, but some work will still be required.
While I didn't follow through every single calculation, I really enjoyed the
book overall and should try to read additional stuff by this author.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Code Breaker&amp;quot; by Walter Isaacson - a biography of Jennifer Doudna,
focusing on the discovery of CRISPR, the competition around it, the ethical
implications of gene editing and COVID vaccine research. An OK book overall,
with some really tedious parts; not the best Isaacson, in my experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;An Immense World&amp;quot; by Ed Yong - secondary title &amp;quot;How Animal Senses Reveal
the Hidden Realms Around Us&amp;quot;; an information-packed book with a huge scope,
describing the sensing capabilities animals possess beyond the human range.
Very interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Mansfield Park&amp;quot; by Jane Austen - familiar style and topic - the lives of
the bored 19th century English gentry. I liked this book less than others
by Austen I read; the characters aren't as well developed (I feel like there
are too many? Austen seems to have neglected to provide distinct roles for
several), and the first half of the book is fairly dull.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;How to Avoid a Climate Disaster&amp;quot; by Bill Gates - a decent overview of the
current state of global warming, and what it would take to avoid the
worst-case scenario. This book could be much better, IMHO, if it had more
depth and a coherent summary/plan. I'm also surprised by the relatively
shallow coverage of nuclear (fission) power, given the importance attributed
to it by Gates. Also, the coverage of carbon capture is surprisingly minimal.
On the good side, I really liked the concept of &amp;quot;green premium&amp;quot; and how to
factor that into economically realistic solutions. This is one of those
subjects that's moving so fast, however, that it needs a fresh treatment
every few years. This book is from 2020 and already some information feels
stale due to the huge progress in solar deployments that's been made in the
past few years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;On Writing: A Memoir of the Craft&amp;quot; by Stephen King - a mix of autobiography
with some advice on writing creative fiction. Very good overall. King's
relationship with his family is inspiring and endearing - not the usual
celebrity fare. One small gripe is that the book is artificially inflated with
some tangential interviews at the end, so it's actually shorter than
advertised.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Engineering in Plain Sight&amp;quot; by Grady Hillhouse - the author is well-known
from his YouTube channel &amp;quot;Practical Engineering&amp;quot;, and this book is a text
presentation of many of the topics he discusses in his videos. The writing
is unmistakable in Hillhouse's enthusiastic style and the illustrations are
beautiful. In all, a very nice book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Children of Time&amp;quot; by Adrian Tchaikovsky - first part of a sci-fi trilogy
about space-faring humans and... spiders. Highly imaginative and fun to read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Journeys North: The Pacific Crest Trail&amp;quot; by Barney Scout Mann - a memoir
of a person thru-hiking the full PCT in 2007, and some stories about his
fellow hikers. Great book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Final Frontiersman&amp;quot; by James Campbell - subtitle is &amp;quot;Heimo Korth and
His Family, Alone in Alaska's Arctic Wilderness&amp;quot;. Very nice biography about
a fur trapper family living in a remote self-built cabin in north-east Alaska.
Covers a period roughly from the 1980s to the early 2000s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Naked Economics&amp;quot; by Charles Wheelan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The count of Monte Cristo&amp;quot; by Alexandre Dumas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Skunk Works: A Personal Memoir of My Years of Lockheed&amp;quot; by Ben Rich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of reading: April - June 2024</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2024/summary-of-reading-april-june-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-06-30T07:38:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-01T01:40:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2024-06-30:/2024/summary-of-reading-april-june-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;River of the Gods: Genius, Courage, and Betrayal in the Search for the
Source of the Nile&amp;quot; by Candice Millard - while the book is readable, I found
it disappointing because it focuses much more on the personalities involved
and their numerous feuds than on the actual exploration, geography and history …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;River of the Gods: Genius, Courage, and Betrayal in the Search for the
Source of the Nile&amp;quot; by Candice Millard - while the book is readable, I found
it disappointing because it focuses much more on the personalities involved
and their numerous feuds than on the actual exploration, geography and history
of the region. The scientific parts of the book would comfortably fit into a
couple of pages - the rest is fluff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;We have no idea&amp;quot; by J. Cham and D. Whiteson - a whimsical and introductory
look at the state of modern physics - what we know, and more importantly -
what we don't know. The book is pretty good, but is full of potty humor and
endless childish puns which I found distracting. It also adds comics
drawings on almost every page for the entertainment factor,
without adding information. I suppose these are good to try to lure kids to
read it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Quantum computing explained - for beginners&amp;quot; by Pantheon Space Academy - this
is certainly the worst book I've read in the last year or more. I honestly
don't undestand how it managed to get this many positive reviews on Amazon,
unless it's some sort of mistake - or scam. The book is a tedious, repetitive
jumble of ever-changing, shallow analogies trying to explain concepts from
quantum computing. Except that it doesn't really explain anything; it mostly
tries to teach the jargon - the kind of understanding that makes you seem
knowledgeable at cocktail parties. There's not a single equation in this book,
not a single algorithm or circuit, not a single snippet of code. I still think
it's some sort of scam. It can't even be AI generated, because any modern
LLM will give you much more useful information in your first 10 minutes of
interaction than this book contains in its entirety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Lions of Al-Rassan&amp;quot; by Guy Gavriel Kay - not my usual fare! A dip into
the world of historic fantasy. The plot is loosely based on the period of
the Spanish reconquista, but everything is changed - the names, the
religions, even the celestial bodies (two moons); some magic is also mixed
in, though in very mild amounts. Good, high-paced story in most places,
though I found the protagonists to be too idealized and some of the
dialogues long and tedious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Boyd: The Fighter Pilot Who Changed the Art of War&amp;quot; by Robert Coram - the
biography of John Boyd, an air-force fighter pilot (roughly between the
Korean war and Vietnam war) that later made significant contribution to
aircraft design (particularly F-15 and F-16) and the theory of conducting
military operations. Very interesting book overall, with insights about
how large organizations work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Slow Productivity&amp;quot; By Cal Newport - a reshuffle of the author's ideas
from &amp;quot;Deep work&amp;quot;, served as &amp;quot;how to work less and achieve more&amp;quot; advice. Way
too general, IMHO, and thus of limited usefulness. The book is short, at
least, but the author apparently struggled to fill it up because it contains
so many barely-relevant detours. I really find cherry-picked stories about
notable people unconvincing because of the huge selection bias inherent in
them. The author even admits this in one scenario towards the end of the
book (&amp;quot;I knew so many professors who took a sabbatical to focus on something
new but never accomplished anything&amp;quot;). Unfortunately, among Newport's books
I've read so far, this is certainly my least favorite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Interplanetary Robots&amp;quot; by Rod Pyle - a good overview of the robotic space
missions sent by humanity up until the Perseverance rover (the book was
written before it launched). Good writing and a decent amount of technical
detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Quantum: Einstein, Bohr and the Great Debate about the nature of reality&amp;quot;
by Manjit Kumar - a historical account of the development of quantum
mechanics, focusing on its philosiphical meaning and the opposing views held
by Einstein and Bohr. I liked this book - it describes the history and
scientists involved in it well and doesn't shy away from some actual physics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Quantum Computing for Everyone&amp;quot; by Chris Bernhardt - a short and effective
introduction to QC. This is a very good book! Starting with only some basic
familiarity with linear algebra concepts, the book develops the fundamentals
of QC methodically and at just the right pace. I wish it was longer, and also
wish the author did fewer simplifications - for example, hadn't omitted the
use of complex numbers. The author clearly has a talent for explaining
technical, math-heavy material; in fact, this is one of the things that
impressed me most about this book and is something I intend to learn from.
The book's language is very terse, logically organized and yet simple! It's
like reading the Simple English version of Wikipedia; no nonsense or useless
detours, no embellishments; few and well-placed analogies. A fantastic example
for anyone writing such material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Mr. Popper's Penguins&amp;quot; by Richard and Florence Atwater - a somewhat silly
but good-natured children's book about a small-town house painter raising
a family of penguins. This is a rare case where I think I liked the movie
version more, even though the plot is very different from the book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Anxious Generation: How the Great Rewiring of Childhood Is Causing
an Epidemic of Mental Illness&amp;quot; by Jonathan Haidt - the author reports on
the sharp decline in mental health of teens and pre-teens (especially girls)
since 2010, and provides compelling evidence that a combination of smartphones
and social media is the most likely cause. The book is fairly troubling, and
certainly thought-provoking. The tangential observations on the challenges
faced by Gen Z folks are also insightful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Something Deeply Hidden: Quantum Worlds and the Emergence of Spacetime&amp;quot; by
Sean Carroll - the book's main goal is to explain the many-worlds theory of
quantum mechanics. It does so reasonably well, but otherwise contains a lot
of other information that seems to be poorly organized and only loosely
related to this main goal. I'd say that the first third of the book was
insightful, and the rest so so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Die With Zero&amp;quot; by Bill Perkins - it's hard to read FI/RE-related discussions
these days without running into mentions of &amp;quot;Die With Zero&amp;quot;, so I decided to
give this book a try. In a sign of just how affluent modern society has
become, the author preaches not over-saving, and instead using one's savings
earlier in life when one still has the physical and mental capacity to enjoy
the experiences money can buy. It's an interesting premise, but IMHO the book
is mainly of inspirational value - as opposed to practical value. The author
tries to develop the idea of &amp;quot;peak savings&amp;quot; but it could certainly use more
work, with more details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Working Poor: Invisible in America&amp;quot; by David K. Shipler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Magic of Reality&amp;quot; by Richard Dawkins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;A Philosophy of Software Design&amp;quot; by John Ousterhout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;All Quiet on the Western Front&amp;quot; by Erich Maria Remarque&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of reading: January - March 2024</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2024/summary-of-reading-january-march-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-03-31T22:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-01T12:46:43-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2024-03-31:/2024/summary-of-reading-january-march-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Lessons in Chemistry: A Novel&amp;quot; by Bonnie Garmus - a research chemist finds
her way in the world following multiple personal tragedies and facing extreme
gender discrimination. I have some mixed feelings about this book. On one hand
it's original, enternaining, well-written and thought provoking. On the
other hand it's full …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Lessons in Chemistry: A Novel&amp;quot; by Bonnie Garmus - a research chemist finds
her way in the world following multiple personal tragedies and facing extreme
gender discrimination. I have some mixed feelings about this book. On one hand
it's original, enternaining, well-written and thought provoking. On the
other hand it's full of shallow plot twists and extreme characters tuned all
the way to 11. I sort of understand some of this is done on purpose to make a
point, maybe a bit like in &amp;quot;Atlas Shrugged&amp;quot;; that said, this book is here 60
years after the period it tries to cover, so I'm not sure that applies. Oh,
and the dog is certainly my favorite character!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Network Effect&amp;quot; by Martha Wells - book 5 of the &amp;quot;Murderbot Diaries&amp;quot; series,
this one a full-length novel. Murderbot and some of his human &amp;quot;clients&amp;quot; go
on another mission, meet old friends and get close to dying - the usual plot.
I found it mostly tedious, because all the original concepts were already
covered in the earlier books. On the other hand, without reading 1-4, this one
would probably be too confusing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Game Over: How Nintendo Conquered The World&amp;quot; David Sheff - the story of
Nintendo, how it evolved from a card-producing family business in 1889 to a
video game empire in the late 20th century. A nice, imformative read, though
having been written in 1993 the book shows its age. It also spends way too
much time on lawsuits and not enough time on the underlying technology, IMO.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;G-Man: J. Edgar Hooever and the Making of the American Century&amp;quot; by Beverly
Gage - a Pulitzer-winning biography of Hoover; long and detailed. Through
Hoover, this books provides many interesting insights into important events
in the US during the mid 20-th century. Even though the author is clearly
biased, she manages her bias well and tries to keep the writing as objective
as possible overall - this is something I appreciated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Wager: A Tale of Shipwreck, Mutiny and Murder&amp;quot; by David Grann - the story
of a famous shipwreck of a British man-of-war in Patagonia in the mid-1700s.
I listened to the audiobook and the narrator was somewhat over-dramatic, but
otherwise the book is interesting and enjoyable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;On the Banks of Plum Creek&amp;quot; by Laura Ingalls Wilder - the next book in the
&amp;quot;little prairie&amp;quot; series; here Laura and her family live on a farm in
Minnesota, the girls going to school and Pa trying to grow wheat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Salt, Fat, Acid, Heat: Mastering the Elements of Good Cooking&amp;quot; by Samin Nosrat
- the author was a chef in upscale restraurants and then turned to writing
about cooking. This book is not a cookbook in the usual sense - at least half
of it is dedicated to explaining how cooking works. I liked the scientific
explanations - while not too deep, they're really useful. The recipes in
this book are all on the fancy / complicated side but there's a lot of general
knowledge here that is important and can be applied in day-to-day cooking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;We've arrived!&amp;quot; by Gregory Khait - (read in Russian) another collection of
short stories focued around Jewish immigrants from the Soviet Union to the
USA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Warmth of Other Suns: The Epic Story of America's Great Migration&amp;quot; by
Isabel Wilkerson - a glimpse into the migration of black Americans from the
Southern states to the North between WWI and the 1970s. Told through the
stories of three migrants with several detours into other stories. Nice,
informative book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Log from the Sea of Cortez&amp;quot; by John Steinbeck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Shadows of forgotten ancestors&amp;quot; by Carl Sagan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Don Quixote&amp;quot; by Miguel Cervantes - found it very tedious this time, barely
managed to finish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of reading: October - December 2023</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/summary-of-reading-october-december-2023/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-12-31T21:40:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T14:25:07-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2023-12-31:/2023/summary-of-reading-october-december-2023/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Nomadland: Surviving America in the Twenty-First Century&amp;quot; by Jessica
Bruder - describes the lives of the modern van-dwellers, mostly of older
adults that travel around the country between seasonal jobs and live in
their RVs or cars. Interesting book that tells a good story and avoids being
preachy most of the …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Nomadland: Surviving America in the Twenty-First Century&amp;quot; by Jessica
Bruder - describes the lives of the modern van-dwellers, mostly of older
adults that travel around the country between seasonal jobs and live in
their RVs or cars. Interesting book that tells a good story and avoids being
preachy most of the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Oxygen: The molecule that made the world&amp;quot; by Nick Lane - one of Lane's
earliest books. Like the others, it's a packed whirlwhind tour of
biochemistry, loaded with enough information to cover a couple of graduate
courses and enough ideas to kick-start a hundred new research projects.
The pace is brutal - blink and you miss it; for anyone with deep interest
in the covered subjects, it's probably worth reading this book several times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Catalyst: How to change anyone's mind&amp;quot; by Jonah Berger - the signal to
noise ratio here is rather low, but it includes some interesting and useful
ideas so a worthwhile read overall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Case of Comrade Tulayev&amp;quot; by Victor Serge - a tale about the great terror
era in the Soviet Union; a government official is randomly assassinated by a
disgruntled student, and this leads to a series of arbitrary arrests and
executions of people across many levels of power. Not an easy book to read,
but pretty good overall for anyone interested in that era.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;An Elegant Defense: The Extraordinary New Science of the Immune System: A
Tale in Four Lives&amp;quot; by Matt Richtel - a journalist's (non-scientist) approach
to describing the immune system and some of the recent advances in medical
care enabled by a better understanding of this critical part of the body.
The actual technical descriptions here are certainly inferior to Dettmer's
&amp;quot;Immune&amp;quot; book, but there's more focus on the human angle, so the book is
also interesting and a decent read. Caveat lector - if you hypochondric, the
descriptions of people suffering from cancer or auto-immune diseases in this
book are quite graphic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Age of Dinosaurs&amp;quot; by Steve Brusatte - a young readers edition of the
author's book about the history of the dinosaurs. Excellent book - very well
organized and methodical, and reflects the state of research until just a
few years ago with many new discoveries in the last decades.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Lights Out: Pride, Delusion and the Fall of General Electric&amp;quot; by Thomas
Gryta and Ted Mann - chronicles the last 20 years or so at GE. Sobering read
about the difficulty of running huge conglomerates and the effects certain
leadership policies have on their future. Also seems to be an example of
a strong focus on immediate returns to investors (via stock buybacks and
dividends) causing significant drain for the company in the long term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;On Immunity: An Innoculation&amp;quot; by Eula Biss - a markedly odd book, which on
the surface tries not to offer any opinion - just the author's experience
raising her son from infancy and the dilemmas she faced w.r.t. immunizations.
Wrapped in a lot of personal stories about her own family that have little
to do with the subject, it's not easy to find actual arguments in this book.
I think the author's strategy is to subtly nudge anti-vaxxers to realize that
their fears are unfounded, and as such it's a valiant attempt. Hopefully it
works in reality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Long Haul: A trucker's tales of life of the road&amp;quot; by Finn Murphy -
a long-haul packing and moving driver, of the kind that moves the contents
of houses across the nation. An amusing set of stories about life on the road,
difficult work schedules and all kinds of odd situations these people
encounter. It was interesting to read about the state of deep focus movers
have while packing their trailers - sounds very familiar for engineers
enjoying the state of &amp;quot;flow&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow&amp;quot; by Gabrielle Zevin - a novel about
a pair of friends making computer games together in the 1990s and early 2000s.
Sam and Sadie are childhood friends who graduated from playing games together
to starting a game development company during their college years.
I liked the first 2/3rds of the book, but not the last 1/3rd - its plot
twists seemed banal in one sense, and entirely unnecessary in another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Mapping the Deep&amp;quot; by Robert Kunzig - a history of oceanography, with
accessible descriptions of the most prominent research in this field up to
the year 2000. Very good book - easy to read while providing a trove of
interesting information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Murderbot Diaries, Books 1-4&amp;quot; by Martha Wells - a collection of sci-fi
novellas about a self-aware humanoid security bot that wants to become
indepdendent and is addicted to binge-watching soap operas. The novellas in
this collections are &amp;quot;All Systems Red&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Artificial Condition&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Rogue
Protocol&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Exit Strategy&amp;quot;. They all follow a somewhat similar trajectory
with long action scenes that are moderately tiresome. Overall it's a nice
story with some thought-provoking concepts and ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The unknown about the known&amp;quot; by Gregory Khait - (read in Russian) a collection
of short stories, written by a relative. It's a mix of non-fiction (both
factual and speculative), fiction and humor on a diverse selection of topics
ranging from the moon race to semi-biographical accounts of jury dury in SF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Stories of Your Life and Others&amp;quot; by Ted Chiang - a collection of sci-fi
short stories. Very original, imaginative writing! The author is not playing
it safe and takes risks; some of the stories are definitely thought provoking,
but some border on the absurd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Endurance: Shackleton's Incredible Voyage&amp;quot; by Alfred Lansing - a classic
account of Shackleton's failed expedition to Antarctica in 1914, when their
ship was stuck in ice and had to be abandoned, followed which the crew spent
a harrowing 1.5 years on ice and the open sea in horrific conditions. The
book is beautifully written and will really make you appreciate your warm,
dry bed at night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Mistakes that worked&amp;quot; by Charlotte Foltz Jones - a short, fun book aimed
at young readers about all kinds of inventions that came about accidentally.
I wish the book was a bit longer with some more details on the science, but
perhaps it's just sufficient for the attention span of kids.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Dreaming in Code&amp;quot; by Scott Rosenberg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;What you should know about politics... but don't&amp;quot; by Jessamyn Conrad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of reading: July - September 2023</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/summary-of-reading-july-september-2023/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-09-30T05:43:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-30T12:47:36-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2023-09-30:/2023/summary-of-reading-july-september-2023/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Ordinary Wolves&amp;quot; by Seth Kantner - a fictional account about coming of age
as a subsistence hunter and fur trader in remote Alaska wilderness in the
1970s and 80s. Since I've read &amp;quot;A thousand trails home&amp;quot; already, the plot is
very familiar - the author projected a lot of his own autobiography …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Ordinary Wolves&amp;quot; by Seth Kantner - a fictional account about coming of age
as a subsistence hunter and fur trader in remote Alaska wilderness in the
1970s and 80s. Since I've read &amp;quot;A thousand trails home&amp;quot; already, the plot is
very familiar - the author projected a lot of his own autobiography here.
Overall the book is good, but the language is too convoluted and artsy in my
opinion - plain writing would have made the book much better. Of the two,
the non-fiction &amp;quot;A thousand trails home&amp;quot; is much better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Julia Child - An extraordinary life in words and pictures&amp;quot; by Erin Hagar and
Joanna Gorham - a short, beautifully illustrated biography of Julia Child
for young readers. As mentioned before, I really enjoy reading books for young
readers once in a while because they deliver the same information with much
less fluff; not being beholden to the same minimum lengths as adult books,
the signal-to-noise ratio is much higher. This book is a great example, if you
want to learn about Julia Child in detail in just a couple of hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Endurance: My year in space and how I got there&amp;quot; by Scott Kelly - an
autobiography by the NASA astronaut who spent a year on board the ISS as part
of a scientific experiment. This is the young readers edition, though still
quite hefty at 300 pages. Nice book, with lots of interesting details about
the careers and daily work of astronauts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Death's End&amp;quot; by Cixin Liu - the closing chapter in the &amp;quot;Three-Body Problem&amp;quot;
trilogy. Of the whole series, I liked this book the least, by far. It may
still be worth reading just for the closure, but IMHO some parts of it
are moving too fast, others way to slow, and a lot of it is just... too
weird.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Or and Alexandra&amp;quot; by Isaac Noy - (read in Hebrew) a youth novel about a
blind boy and his relationships with classmates, teachers and others. An OK
book that consistently overdoes it with flowery language, maybe for
educational purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Eccentric Orbits: The Iridium Story&amp;quot; by John Bloom - the history of the
Iridium satellite project, focusing on the struggle to keep it alive after
Motorola decided to shut it down in the late 1990s. Very good writing with
tons of interesting technical and business information. The parts about
negotiations to secure funding did get a bit tedious, but I do highly
recommend the book overall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Song of the Cell: An Exploration of Medicine and the New Human&amp;quot; by
Siddhartha Mukherjee - the latest book of the cancer-researcher-turned-writer.
Here Mukherjee starts with describing animal cells, how they were discovered
and covering different cell types in the body, leading into discussions of
diseases (focusing on cancer). Pretty good book; the cell biology didn't feel
particularly in-depth (nowhere near Nick Lane's level), but it ties several
disciplines together fairly well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Coming back Alive&amp;quot; by Spike Walker - the story of an epic rescue mission by
the US coast guard in Alaska in the 1990s. Provides some general information
about how the coast guard works in that area; alas, it mostly focuses on one
mission, which makes it a bit tedious to my taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;CORS in Action&amp;quot; by Monsur Hossain - a short book (booklet, really) describing
CORS, with examples for both the client and server side. The book does a good
job, but has two glaring issues: first, it's almost 10 years old at this
point and things have changed. XHR is not used as much as &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;fetch&lt;/tt&gt; these
days, and there's less need for workarounds for clunky versions of IE. Second,
it tries really hard to fill space in order to qualify as a book, but really
the core contents could fit in a longish blog post. Many of the explanations
are long-drawn, with detours and tables comparing HTTP methods, etc.
Thankfully the book is still short so it's not too daunting to scan through
these. All that said, it's a useful, comprehensive resource to learn about
CORS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Unbearable Lightness of Being&amp;quot; by Milan Kundera - a novel set around
the 1968 Prague spring, mostly following the romantic travails of 3-4
protagonists. I'm sure that when this book was originally published in the
early 80s, it was considered very avant-garde for the poignant criticism
of the communist party, the philosophical sprinkling and the explicit sexual
details, but I personally found it a chore and couldn't wait for it to end.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Opposite of Spoiled&amp;quot; by Ron Liebler - the subtitle is &amp;quot;Raising Kids Who
Are Grounded, Generous, and Smart About Money&amp;quot; and it's a good summary of
what the book is about. It's a collection of relevant topics with varying
quality; I found the book to be scannered and not overly insightful, but it
does have a couple of good points that are worth thinking about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Chasing Space&amp;quot; by Leland Melvin - another astronaut autobiography. Nice read
overall; it would be even better if he spent a bit more time talking about
the details of his space missions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Shrinks: The Untold Story of Psychiatry&amp;quot; by Jeffrey Lieberman - a very
interesting history of Psychiatry as a science and clinical specialization,
focusing on the 20th century.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Finding me&amp;quot; by Viola Davis - the acclaimed acctress's autobiography,
focusing on her difficult childhood. Very good, powerful book; especially the
first 2/3rds or so. The writing is also very genuine, almost feels raw and
unedited in some places. Every semi-famous person seems to be writing books
these days through shadow writers; something tells me that Viola Davis didn't
use one for this book, and that's commendable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Eloquent JavaScript, 3rd edition&amp;quot; by Marijn Haverbeke&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Cosmos&amp;quot; by Carl Sagan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Masters of Doom&amp;quot; by David Kushner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Little House on the Prairie&amp;quot; by Laura Ingalls Wilder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of reading: April - June 2023</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/summary-of-reading-april-june-2023/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-30T16:14:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-30T23:16:27-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2023-06-30:/2023/summary-of-reading-april-june-2023/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;WebAssembly: The Definitive Guide&amp;quot; by Brian Sletten - a wide and shallow
overview of the WASM landscape. Logically, it can be seen as a compantion to
&amp;quot;The Art of WebAssembly&amp;quot; which goes deep into the WASM language and spec;
in reality, it falls short. The book is full of laborious explanations …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;WebAssembly: The Definitive Guide&amp;quot; by Brian Sletten - a wide and shallow
overview of the WASM landscape. Logically, it can be seen as a compantion to
&amp;quot;The Art of WebAssembly&amp;quot; which goes deep into the WASM language and spec;
in reality, it falls short. The book is full of laborious explanations
of computer basics, teaches basic C, basic Rust, etc. It's not clear if the
book is meant for actual programmers or for non-technical folks getting
the lay of the land. There's no depth in the code samples either - it's just
a collection of &amp;quot;Hello World&amp;quot;-level snippets gathered from the introduction
pages of documentation. It pains me to write such a negative review of a
technical book - clearly there was a lot of effort put into this one; that
said, it's just not worth the time, IMHO.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Dark Sun: The Making of the Hydrogen Bomb&amp;quot; by Richard Rhodes - a detailed
history of the emergence of H bombs in both the USA and USSR, though it could
equally accurately be called &amp;quot;The story of Soviet espionage in the US nuclear
program&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;How the Soviets developed their nuclear weapons&amp;quot;. In fact, these
two subjects probably get much more coverage in the book than its title
subject. The book is good, but more details on the actual physics and
engineering of H bombs would make it great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;What Do You Care What Other People Think?&amp;quot; by Richard Feynman - additional
stories from Feynman's life; this is a sequel to &amp;quot;Surely you're joking&amp;quot;.
While some of the stories in this book are fun and new, some others overlap
with the previous book quite a bit. The part on the Challenger disaster
investigation is very long and takes up a good chunk of the book. Overall I
enjoyed the book, though it's clearly approaching the threshold of diminishing
returns for sequels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Inventor&amp;quot; by Gersh Taicher - (read in Russian) the next installment of this
autobiographic tale, focusing on the late 1980s and early 90s, when the author
created a company for well logging using nuclear magnetic resonance and tried
other inventions with similar approaches. I liked this book a bit more than
the previous one; it discusses the creative process in an insightful way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Things to make and do in the 4th dimension&amp;quot; by Matt Parker - a tour of
various mathematical topics the author finds interesting, written in an
accessible and conversational way. While the book's title mentions 4D and
the author tries to dedicate some chapters to this topic, it's not a big part
of the book and I didn't find those parts super insightful (4D is just hard!),
though overall the book is not bad. Not amazing, but not bad either.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Christianity: The First Three Thousand Years&amp;quot; by Diarmaid MacCulloch - a
very long history of Christianity from its inception and until the early 21st
century. Overall, I found this book tedious and unsatisfactory. The first
third or so - dealing with very early Christianity and its origins - is pretty
bad, IMHO. Its organization is a mess, bouncing from topic to topic, with very
little evidence provided for anything. It may be the case that indeed early
Christianity just isn't very well documented; unfortunately, this was the
part I was most interested in. The rest of the book is somewhat better and
more readable (probably because it has actual written sources to rely on), but
still not great. I'm relieved to be done with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Failure Is Not an Option: Mission Control From Mercury to Apollo 13
and Beyond&amp;quot; by Gene Kranz - autobiographic book by the NASA flight director
who ran many of the famous lunar missions, including Apollo 11 and 13. Very
detailed, in-depth account of how mission control works and the various
problems they grapple with. When space missions are celebrated it's usually
the astronauts and engineers in the limelight, but mission control plays
a critical role too - and this book is good at explaining why.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;A Thousand Trails Home&amp;quot; by Seth Kantner - an auto-biographic story of the
author's growing up in the family of subsistence hunters in the remote
north-west of Alaska, mixed with tidbits about Alaskan history, the changes
undergoing the state's landscape, animals and population, as well as a few
Caribou recipes. Excellent book, highly recommended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Infinite Staircase&amp;quot; by Geoffrey A. Moore - a grand theory of everything
with the author trying to create a coherent philosophy of living rooted in
modern secular values. Valiant attempt, but IMHO completely misses the mark. I
found this book to be very tedious and don't recommend it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Fire in the Valley: The Birth and Death of the Personal Computer&amp;quot; by Michael
Swaine, Paul Freiberger - this book is alright, but it would be much better
if it focused on the technical details rather than MBA stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;On Call in the Arctic&amp;quot; by Thomas J. Sims - an autobiographical account of
a doctor's 16-month assignment in Nome, Alaska in the early 1970s. Very
interesting and well-told stories of local life, though it does feel like the
author has a tendency for tall talking. Also, if you're easily grossed out
by medical details, this book is probably not for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;how to: Absurd Scientific Advice for Common Real-World Problems&amp;quot; by Randall
Munroe - somewhat similar idea to &amp;quot;What if&amp;quot;, but from a slightly different
direction. Munroe gets to pick the subject and examine it from multiple
angles. Another fun book!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Dark Forest&amp;quot; by Cixin Liu - part 2 of the &amp;quot;Three body problem&amp;quot; trilogy.
I liked this part even more than the first one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Surely you're joking, Mr. Feynman!&amp;quot; by Richard Feynman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;What If?&amp;quot; by Randall Munroe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Interpreter of Maladies&amp;quot; by Jhumpa Lahiri&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of reading: January - March 2023</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/summary-of-reading-january-march-2023/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-03-31T20:26:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-01T03:28:51-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2023-03-31:/2023/summary-of-reading-january-march-2023/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Nine: Inside the secret world of the Supreme Court&amp;quot; by Jeffrey Toobin - a
detailed survey of the Supreme Court's justices, their selection process and
key cases from the mid 1980s and until ~2007 or so. Very interesting look
inside the works of the court that helps one understand how …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Nine: Inside the secret world of the Supreme Court&amp;quot; by Jeffrey Toobin - a
detailed survey of the Supreme Court's justices, their selection process and
key cases from the mid 1980s and until ~2007 or so. Very interesting look
inside the works of the court that helps one understand how it operates.
Unfortunately, the book is author to remain politically neutral, although he
seems to be trying to. IMHO this book could be much more powerful and
impressive if it didn't have a political agenda in the background.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Three-Body Problem&amp;quot; by Cixin Liu - a pretty good work of science fiction,
very original. It's refreshing to read a book where the plot doesn't circle
around the US, the protagonists aren't American or European and not everyone
speaks English. I also felt like the book teaches a bit of history about China
in the 1960s-1980s, and has additional - more global - political overtones
talking about extreme environmentalism leading to self-loathing and striving
for destroying humanity. The science fiction aspect of the book is
wide-ranging, from Martian-style hard science fiction, to completely
fantastical dreams. The mixing up of technological levels is a bit jarring - a
society that can unfurl fundamental particles into different dimensions and
communicate across the universe using quantum entanglement surely will have
better computing paradigms than etching VLSI circuits with PN junctions onto
2D surfaces, right? That aside, I did enjoy the book quite a bit and will read
the next part.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Way Things Work Now&amp;quot; by David Macaulay - a large, illustrated book that
explains how much of modern technology works, with detailed hand-drawn
diagrams and a bunch humor using silly mammoths. While the diagrams are really
great, the book is often quite shallow. It does serve its main goal - to keep
kids engated while learning about technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Birds, Beasts and Relatives&amp;quot; by Gerald Durrell - book 2 of the Corfu trilogy,
detailing some additional adventures the author had with his family.
Interestingly, many of the stories here (both human and animal) are...
reproduction-oriented, I guess? Not sure if it's accidental or aims to
represent the protagonist's age and thought process in some way. One of the
funniest books I've read in a long while.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;What If? 2&amp;quot; by Randall Munroe - additional questions answered; these are a
bit more esoteric on average, but still fun to read with a good mix of hard
science and humor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Good Prose: The Art of Nonfiction&amp;quot; by Tracy Kidder and Richart Todd - in this
book the Pulitzer-winning author Kidder and his long-time editor share their
thoughts and experience in writing and editing nonfiction articles and books.
It's a nice read if you want to learn how writing happens in real life; if
you're looking for tips on writing nonfiction, this book won't be of much use
IMHO.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Handprints on Hubble&amp;quot; by Kathryn D. Sullivan - one of the space shuttle
astronauts tells about her career, focusing on her role in the development
and launch of the Hubble space telescope. Very comprehensive book with lots of
interesting details, particularly w.r.t. serviceability in space and how they
planned and trained for it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Bond Investing for Dummies, 3rd edition&amp;quot; by Russell Wild - a very detailed
and thorough book, and I found the advice given in it sound overall; the
author's general investing philisophy seems well aligned with mine (not just
on bonds). It's up-to-date (published in mid-2022), but the author didn't
spend much time talking about the bond market in 2022 - which turned out to be
unusual. I can sort of understand the ommission - the book wants to stay
relevant for years to come - but this is my only criticism. Otherwise, very
solid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;A Brief History of Time&amp;quot; by Stephen Hawking - I'm quite sure I've read this
one before, but it was more than 20 years ago so there's no record. Hawking
is a prominent theoretical physicist that described the process by which black
holes emit radiation (now called Hawking radiation); he wrote this book &amp;quot;for
people without physics background&amp;quot;, trying to explain modern physics from its
beginnings and all the way to advanced origin-of-the-universe topics. The book
is well written and interesting, but many parts of it are still extremely
dense and require a physics degree to decipher. The book also shows its age,
as several important discoveries were made after 1988 (for example - the
detection of gravitational waves).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Atoms in the Family&amp;quot; by Laura Fermi - a biography of Enrico Fermi, written
by his wife. Starts with Fermi's childhood, through his career in Italy and
the move to the USA with stops in NY, Chicago and Los Alamos. The writing is
straight-to-the-point and unadorned, which is a refreshing change from typical
professional biographers. Pretty good book overall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Art of WebAssembly&amp;quot; by Rick Battagline - a nice introduction to
programming in WASM. This book focuses on the WASM language itself (the
textual format), discussing many aspects of its usage and interaction with
the JS host environment (in the browser or Node.js); there are numerous code
samples to try and experiment with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Where the Crawdads Sing&amp;quot; by Delia Owens - a lightweight mystery novel
about a woman who grew up alone in the marshes of the North Carolina
coast, having been abandoned by her family from a very young age. The mystery
plot is a bit weak, but the descriptions of the flora and fauna of the region
make for a pleasant reading overall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Emigrant&amp;quot; by Gersh Taicher - (read in Russian) a family member recommended
this book - an autobiographic account of an emigrant from the USSR to Israel
in the 1970s. The book is entertaining, humorous, and likely interesting
for people with the right background. I did find the writing to be somewhat
too self-centric, however. Granted, this is an autobiography, but I've read
many of those and something's a bit off here. Perhaps everyone is
self-centered, and the author is just being more honest than average? Another
observation is how rooted the author's world-view is in his USSR past; it's
quite remarkable, really, given that he left there at 26 and wrote this book
in his late 60s. This is very interesting to ponder w.r.t. when our brains
mature and get &amp;quot;set&amp;quot; for life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;How we got to the Moon&amp;quot; by John Rocco - one of those rare gems you find while
randomly browsing the science section of a public library with your kids. In
this book the author presents a detailed description of the Apollo 11 mission,
focusing on all the science, engineering and training that went into it. The
information is distilled enough to be understood by middle-schoolers, but
isn't dumbed down. The author presents &amp;quot;problems&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;solutions&amp;quot; and covers
pretty much every aspect of the mission, with details as minute as the design
of the flame deflector for the launch or how thermal insulation between fuel
tanks works. What's most amazing about this book is the colored illustrations
on every page, drawn by the author himself. The illustrations cover everything
from engineering details to the people involved in the mission. Extremely
impressive work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Covenant&amp;quot; by James Michener - historical epic novel about South Africa.
Paints a fairly damning picture of the Afrikaans population leading to
apartheid, and in particular the role fanatical religious zeal played in it.
Interestingly, this book was written in 1980, right before the critical decade
that saw the dissolution of that regime. Like in some of Michener's other
books, he tries to give equal treatment to different eras in terms of book
pages; while this is a noble goal, it doesn't always make sense. Much more is
known about the 20th century than about ancient Xhosa, for example, so the
Xhosa stories end up being long-drawn soap operas while precious little page
budget is dedicated to pivotal historial moments in the last 200 years and
some parts read like a condensed encyclopedia entry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Meltdown: Earthquake, Tsunami, and Nuclear Disaster in Fukushima&amp;quot; by
Deirdre Langeland - a short but detailed and interesting book about the
Fukushima disaster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Omnivore's Dilemma: A Natural History of Four Meals&amp;quot; by Michael Pollan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Unaccustomed Earth&amp;quot; by Jhumpa Lahiri&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;American Moonshot: John F. Kennedy and the Great Space Race&amp;quot; by Douglas
Brinkley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Little House in the Big Woods&amp;quot; by Laura Ingalls Wilder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of reading: October - December 2022</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2022/summary-of-reading-october-december-2022/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-31T22:55:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-07T11:40:34-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2022-12-31:/2022/summary-of-reading-october-december-2022/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Justice for All: Earl Warren and the Nation He Made&amp;quot; - a nice and detailed
biography of Earl Warren.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Silk Roads: A New History of the World&amp;quot; by Peter Frankopak - a fast-paced
whirlwhind of world history from pre-historic times and until the early
2010s, with a focus on central Asia …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Justice for All: Earl Warren and the Nation He Made&amp;quot; - a nice and detailed
biography of Earl Warren.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Silk Roads: A New History of the World&amp;quot; by Peter Frankopak - a fast-paced
whirlwhind of world history from pre-historic times and until the early
2010s, with a focus on central Asia. Not a bad book, though very scattered
given the enormous scope and limited space. What bothers me is that the book's
premise is to re-tell history without focusing on Europe and focusing on Asia
instead; IMHO it fails miserably in this task, still focusing mostly on
Europe, and on Asia only inasmuch as its connection to Europe. More text is
spent on explaining English commercial interests in China than on the history
of China itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;How I Killed Pluto and Why It Had It Coming&amp;quot; by Mike Brown  - an entertaining
story of the astronomical research that led to the demotion of Pluto to
the status of a &amp;quot;dwarf planet&amp;quot;. The author is the astronomer who discovered
the other prominent dwarf planets to date (Eris, Haumea and Makemake), and
this book has more scientific detail than deGrasse Tyson's book on the
same subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Future of Fusion Energy&amp;quot; by J. Parisi and J. Ball -
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2022/book-review-the-future-of-fusion-energy-by-j-parisi-and-j-ball/"&gt;full review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Who We Are and How We Got Here&amp;quot; by David Reich - the author is a researcher
in the domain of population-level DNA analysis, specializing at analyzing
&amp;quot;ancient DNA&amp;quot; from archaeological remains of humans to track the movements
and interactions of human populations in the ancient and more recent past.
This book is a summary of recent research (as of 2018) in this fast-moving
field. It covers several interesting subjects and presents fascinating
findings from very recent research breakthroughts; on the flip side, the
writing style is somewhat dry and overly academic. From reading this book,
it's difficult to discern how speculative the information presented is; some
if it is certainly very new, published in recent papers. An interesting field
of study to keep track of in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Dreams of El Dorado: A History of the American West&amp;quot; by H. W. Brands - a
fast-paced overview of notable events in the history of the Western USA. Nice
read, though necessarily somewhat shallow given the scope.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Learning HTTP/2&amp;quot; by S. Ludin and J. Garza - a very short (barely 100 pages)
book about the performance issues with HTTP/1.1 and how HTTP/2 was designed
to resolve them. Overall it's a nice little book, though I feel the authors
could have beefed it up quite a bit. While the performance discussions are
insightful, I found the explanation of how the HTTP/2 protocol actually works
lacking. More details on that, and perhaps even a simple educational
implementation would go a long way and the book could still be kept to under
200 pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Trial&amp;quot; by Franz Kafka - from time to time I'm giving classics a try.
This book interested me because it begat some cultural memes; it turned out to
be far more weird than I imagined. Towards the end I think I &amp;quot;got&amp;quot; the main
point of it, and it's a powerful - albeit depressing - one, but so much about
the story is bizarre without any obvious connection to the main plot that I
can discern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Immune&amp;quot; by Philipp Dettmer - a description of how the immune system works,
for the layperson. The immune system is incredibly complicated and
intertwined, and scientific understanding of all its details is still far from
perfect, so the author took upon himself an ambitious task. The execution is
pretty good; not amazing, but the book is certainly useful and enjoyable. I
found the general tone somewhat rambly, there are too many analogies and too
few diagrams, but given the complexity of the topic I'm quite happy with the
increased understanding I have after having finished the book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Wonderful Wizard of Oz&amp;quot; by L. Frank Baum - got around to reading this
book end-to-end again with my kids (the last time I read it was maybe 30
years ago). As usual, it's difficult to appreciate books out of their
historical context; for example, old reviews say this was the &amp;quot;first really
American fairytale&amp;quot;, with elements of corn farming and self-made men, as
opposed to the classical fairytales that describe European peasant life of
centuries past. Another observation is how shockingly violent this story is.
When a wild cat is chasing a mouse and the axeman decapitates it without much
thought, my daughter was appalled - the wild cat just wants to eat, why is its
life less important than the mouse's? After all, the Lion was described as
&amp;quot;going into the forest to catch his lunch&amp;quot; just a few pages ago; where's the
justice here? Interestingly, the same review I read pointed out that compared
to the old fairy tales this books is gentle for the &amp;quot;currente generation of
American children&amp;quot;, the &amp;quot;current generation&amp;quot; being 100+ years ago when the
book was first published. It's interesting to ponder this downard progression
in violence in children literature, and how it's correlated humanity's general
progression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Gideon's Trumpet&amp;quot; by Anthony Lewis - tells the story of the landmark
Supreme Court case of Gideon v. Wainwright, that ruled that defendants in
trials have the right to an attorney even if they don't have the means to
afford one. It's really an amazing story - a determined person who
punched way above his weight and affected a significant and lasting change in
the US criminal justice system. The book is very well written - I particularly
enjoyed all the details of the Supreme Court's workings. It's a bit heavy and
academic at times though - probably a very useful read for law students
interested in constitutional law.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Ascent of Money: A Financial History of the World&amp;quot; by Niall Ferguson - an
overview of the roots of the modern financial system. Written in an
entertaining style based on many anecdotes, this book feels like it's biting
off more than it can chew. It's not a bad book, but nothing to rave about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The Pastures of Heaven&amp;quot; by John Steinbeck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Atlas Shrugged&amp;quot; by Ayn Rand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "The Future of Fusion Energy" by J. Parisi and J. Ball</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2022/book-review-the-future-of-fusion-energy-by-j-parisi-and-j-ball/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-10-19T20:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-20T03:29:22-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2022-10-19:/2022/book-review-the-future-of-fusion-energy-by-j-parisi-and-j-ball/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fusion research is back in the news again, due to multiple factors. I've been
long interested in this topic and have seen this book mentioned in several
places since it came out in 2019. Now that I finally got it and read it, I'm
really happy I did. I think …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fusion research is back in the news again, due to multiple factors. I've been
long interested in this topic and have seen this book mentioned in several
places since it came out in 2019. Now that I finally got it and read it, I'm
really happy I did. I think it's likely the best book I've read this year, and
one of the best works of non-fiction in recent memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes the book so great is the combination of scientific, yet undestandable
writing. The authors achieved a level of clarity and organization of thought
that's enviable, particulary for describing a topic of immense essential
complexity like nuclear fusion. It really is very, very well done; the kind of
presentation of a technical topic that I can only strive to achieve in my own
humble writings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book doesn't shy away from equations, but I don't think anything beyond late
high-school math and physics is required for decent understanding. The authors
start from the basics, carefully laying down the foundation, but manage to stave
off boredom by focusing on the big picture at the same time. &amp;quot;Simple&amp;quot; ideas for
a fusion device are presented; then, issues with those designs are discussed and
solutions are proposed. After repeating this process several times, the book
provides a pretty decent description of state-of-the-art devices, including a
detailed overview of what ITER is going to be. All along, the book is written
in such a way that obviates almost all &amp;quot;but why&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;what if&amp;quot; questions, by
laying out multiple alternatives for potential challenges and carefully
discussing them in succession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it focuses mostly on nuclear fusion for electricity power plants, the
book has a few other interesting chapters. For example, the second chapter
is a whirlwind tool of all the potential energy generating methods at
humanity's disposal. Everything is clearly quantified, with nice
back-of-the-envelope calculations. Have you ever wondered just how much total
windpower there is... on Earth? Or, could we satisfy all our needs by
harvesting the energy from waves, or geothermal energy? The book answers
all these questions, and many more. I learned so much just from this chapter, it
alone is worth the cost of the book! Another fascinating chapter talks about
space-travel propulsion and how fusion could be important there as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having read this book (twice in succession, which is something I rarely do,
but it's simply &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; good) I feel much better equipped to understand
the news occasionally published about fusion, including all the press releases
from fusion start-ups. And I've acquired a sobering appreciation for the huge
complexity of the problem fusion scientists and engineers are trying to solve.
If you're interested in science, and in energy science in particular, this book
is really amazing and highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Physics"></category></entry></feed>