<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Eli Bendersky's website - Finance</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/feeds/finance.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://eli.thegreenplace.net/</id><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><entry><title>The economic crash and free markets</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2008/12/04/the-economic-crash-and-free-markets" rel="alternate"></link><published>2008-12-04T08:37:35-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2008-12-04:/2008/12/04/the-economic-crash-and-free-markets</id><summary type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
        I'm having a hard time understanding why many people are blaming the
        free markets for the recent economic crash. The most popular opinion is
        that the government has let the markets "run wild", and it should now
        regulate them more instead. But IMHO, this is the exact opposite of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
        I'm having a hard time understanding why many people are blaming the
        free markets for the recent economic crash. The most popular opinion is
        that the government has let the markets "run wild", and it should now
        regulate them more instead. But IMHO, this is the exact opposite of the
        truth!
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
If anything, this economic crash happened because of &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt;
regulation, not too little. The mortgage loopholes, the whole &lt;em&gt;subprime&lt;/em&gt;
business, was made possible by governmental intervention into the free market.
This resulted in a bubble, and now the bubble has burst and pulls down the whole
economy.
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Circa seven years ago the dot-com bubble has burst and caused a short period of
recession, which hurt most badly the industry that originated it - the hi-tech,
software and internet businesses. This makes lots of sense, and I don't think
anyone serious blamed the free markets for the crash. The free markets (like
most economic theories) work over prolonged periods of time, not over short
few-year spans. The dot-com bubble burst made lots of investors cautious, and a
similar burst is very unlikely any time soon (though it will happen eventually,
since people have short memories. See the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tulip_mania"&gt;tulip mania&lt;/a&gt;, for example). A
few months ago (before the big crash) the NASDAQ index was at 60% of its value
in the peak of the bubble. This is the free market's way of correcting itself.
Some business model seemed successful at one period of time, but (again, as
happens a lot in economics) most investors didn't really know that it was shaky
- a bubble. So the market crashed - it makes sense.
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The same can be said about the latest crisis. Yes, it's deeper, because the
financial and banking industry is much larger and affects much more people than
the internet business. But it was a bubble none-the-less. And moreover, it was
aided &lt;em&gt;caused&lt;/em&gt; by the government's regulation of the loaning business.
And eventually (in a few years, it seems) - the free market will correct itself,
and people will just be more cautious in the future.
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
But the government tries to solve the problem by even more intervention. My
opinion may be unpopular on this subject, but I'm not sure that bailing out
banks is a good idea. It's an incentive to err again in the future, and that
worries me. Brokers who went loose with the inverstors' money that was based on
shaky foundations, and those bankers who've lent money knowing that it won't be
paid, but that they will get the bonus for the deal, won't be careful next time,
&lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; the government has intervened. "The fed will save us again"
they're now saying, and as soon as the crisis ends they'll be back.
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Recently I've heard that the incentives programs of the big governments include
not only saving banks but also real economic incentives for returning to growth.
This is great, but I'm still concerned about the ratio of these expenditures.
Saving banks won't help the economy recover, incentives to the industry and to
consumers will.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry><entry><title>Spending my RentACoder earned money on Books</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/07/13/spending-my-rentacoder-earned-money-on-books" rel="alternate"></link><published>2007-07-13T07:48:45-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2007-07-13:/2007/07/13/spending-my-rentacoder-earned-money-on-books</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
I've earned around $300 from RentACoder when I worked there last month and got
the money transferred to my PayPal account (now that PayPal have solved their
bug which required international users to have a US back account in order to
accept money). I want to spend this money on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
I've earned around $300 from RentACoder when I worked there last month and got
the money transferred to my PayPal account (now that PayPal have solved their
bug which required international users to have a US back account in order to
accept money). I want to spend this money on online shopping, and this means
&lt;b&gt;books!&lt;/b&gt; Unfortunately, Amazon doesn't work with PayPal (because it belongs
to their competitor eBay), so I registered at Barnes &amp; Noble. It is more
expensive than Amazon by 15-20% on average, but I don't have much choice.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

Today I made the first order - "Lisp in Small Pieces" - it's just the kind of
book to buy as a special present to myself. I doubt I would agree to shell out
the $80 it costs had I not had the RAC money in PayPal already. For now it looks
like the transaction was processed successfully and BN pulled the money from my
PayPal account.
&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Finance"></category><category term="Internet"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "A random walk down Wall Street" by B. Malkiel</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/11/28/book-review-a-random-walk-down-wall-street-by-b-malkiel" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-11-28T22:55:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-11-28:/2004/11/28/book-review-a-random-walk-down-wall-street-by-b-malkiel</id><summary type="html">
I ordered this book after reading Joel's positive review (&lt;a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/" rel="nofollow"&gt;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/&lt;/a&gt;). The review ends with:
&lt;p&gt;
What if I told you that you could read one book and know everything you are
going to need to know about managing your investments? And I mean, everything.
Well, it's true. And …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
I ordered this book after reading Joel's positive review (&lt;a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/" rel="nofollow"&gt;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/&lt;/a&gt;). The review ends with:
&lt;p&gt;
What if I told you that you could read one book and know everything you are
going to need to know about managing your investments? And I mean, everything.
Well, it's true. And this is the book. If you can't be bothered to read anything
else about investing, read this one book.
 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Well, I heartily agree. This is probably the best finance/economics book I've
ever read.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Burton Malkiel takes a simple, logical approach, with intuitive mathematical
expositions, statistical studies and numerous examples to explain his view of
the investment practices on the stock market. He analyzes fundamental and
technical analysis and points out their flaws (loaded with historical studies
that prove his point). Then, he presents the random walk theory (efficient
markets) and takes a position as its proponent to some degree. The book
concludes with a guide to investment taken from his own experience.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
There's something very charming in the methodical, determined approach of this
book. Malkiel takes no prisoners with the techniques he criticizes. He presents
studies, both academic and by financial institutions, simulations, discusses
some economics related maths and presents historic evidence to prove his points.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; I'm not sure I agree with Joel on the "only one" part of the review. I'm
glad I've read some investments books before this one, so I can fully grasp
Malkiel's criticism. I can especially relate to the attack on technical
analysis. As I wrote in previous reviews, this technique of investment analysis
seems somewhere from unreal to ridiculous to me, and reading this book just made
this opinion stronger. It's very amusing to read about some of the
occasionally-popping technical analysis gurus, about running computer
simulations with historical data that shatter all the technical "signs" and
about random simulations that contain "head and shoulders", "triple bottoms",
etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The investment plan offered in this book is probably the most
logical and down-to-earth one I've read about. To conclude, go get this book,
it's a terrific review of where you should and shouldn't invest money.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Technical Analysis ..." by J. Murphy</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/07/29/book-review-technical-analysis-by-j-murphy" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-07-29T23:03:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-07-29:/2004/07/29/book-review-technical-analysis-by-j-murphy</id><summary type="html">
        The full name is: "Technical Analysis of the Financial Markets:
A Comprehensive Guide to Trading Methods and Applications"
by John J. Murphy
&lt;p&gt;
Carrying on with my financial education, a serious text on
technical reference was due. After having read a soft primer
on fundamental analysis (Lynch), I felt a need …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        The full name is: "Technical Analysis of the Financial Markets:
A Comprehensive Guide to Trading Methods and Applications"
by John J. Murphy
&lt;p&gt;
Carrying on with my financial education, a serious text on
technical reference was due. After having read a soft primer
on fundamental analysis (Lynch), I felt a need to see
"the other side" as well. There's an Israeli online forum of
stock market enthusiasts I'm following, and most of the discussions
there are "technical" (no doubt because it's the sexiest topic
of stock trading - more on this later). So, I just wanted to
finally understand all those idioms people are using. I mean, I can
grasp what a "trend" is, but when they dive into RSI, stochastics,
Doji candles, continuation head &amp;amp; shoulders, fibonacci retraces and
Eliott's 3rd wave I just feel a need to get myself acquianted with
the whole topic.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
So, after some online searching, I came upon "Technical Analysis of
the Financial Markets" as the de-facto text on the topic. Its first
edition came out somewhere in the 80s, and since then it's definitely
considered as "the one, if you only want to read one book on the topic".
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The book itself is somewhat encyclopedic in nature. Over 500+ pages,
the author presents the theory/applications of technical analysis,
from the best-known methods to some obscure ones. Though there is
probably more to the topic than covered in this text, I'm sure the
99.9% of the things people actually know/use is there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
It starts with a chapter on the philosophy of technical analysis,
and then dives right into the theory. Beginning with the "simplest"
and the most traditional - Dow theory (trends, basic charting),
and going on to charting, reversal/continuation patterns, options/futures,
moving averages, oscillators, Japanese candle-sticks, time series,
and so on. The scope, as I mentioned, is vast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I personally feel that there's too little "philosophy" in this book.
The first chapter is good, and is a must read for everyone who's
interested in stocks, but I think that the rest of the book would use
some "justification" as well. At some point, the impressions is that
"patterns" are thrown at the reader in a rapid pace, without giving time
to think them over, and without even trying to stress the reason _why_
these patterns work. Maybe it's because the book is intended more as
a reference and not as a light-read.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In this review I don't want to go much into my own view of trading
- fundamental vs. technical, etc. I think, however, that this book
should've spent a little more time explaining some of the drawbacks
of techinal analysis, it would be only fair. The amount of information
is overwhelming, and one could be easily fooled to believe that these
are "magic methods" that just work. Naturally, most of the examples
are tailored with perfect patterns. Perhaps more examples which show
how patterns fail, and explain why they fail would be helpful.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Technical analysis is dangerous exactly because of such books - a wealth
of information, "neat tricks" that tell you how stocks will behave.
What is more "cool" - a trader that spends days reading financial reports
(dull !!) of a company prior to deciding about buying their stock, or
someone who fiddles with formulas on a computer, drawing pretty "candles",
"trend lines" and counting fibonacci sequences ? Clearly, the latter
is much more attractive to investors. People want it quick, without too
much hard work. "Just show me the numbers".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
To the defense of the author, I must say that he indeed warns people
of using the techniques frivolously. Applying many analysis techniques
in parallel is recommended, and tips are given on how to manage investment
funds better (how much money to allocate to each trade, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
All in all, the book is useful if you're seriously into trading. Although
technical analysis is definitely no panacea, I think that it can be combined
with fundamentals, and some common sense to produce good results. After all,
though the market is clearly driven not only by sentiments, it's not driven
solely by fundamentals either. Technical elements do play role in the movement
of stocks, and having tools to analyze these elements is important.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry><entry><title>annoying stock market commentaries</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/06/04/annoying-stock-market-commentaries" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-06-04T20:52:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-06-04:/2004/06/04/annoying-stock-market-commentaries</id><summary type="html">
        I'm following the American stock exchange via Yahoo's finance site (finance.yahoo.com) which is well updated and fairly easy to use if you want to keep an eye on some companies.
&lt;p&gt;
But there's something that annoys me immensely about this site. They have a "Top stories" box (to the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        I'm following the American stock exchange via Yahoo's finance site (finance.yahoo.com) which is well updated and fairly easy to use if you want to keep an eye on some companies.
&lt;p&gt;
But there's something that annoys me immensely about this site. They have a "Top stories" box (to the right from the market summary chart) where they post "stories" usually from CBS MarketWatch. These top stories are so dumb I sometimes lough out loud...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
First of all, in a stormy market day, they always lag by a hour or two at least, thus being completely irrelevant (imagine that a weather forecast would be posted once in a two months and stayed posted thgroughout).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Second, and most annoying, they just provide dumb, "backwards" explanations. The gem is as usual the US interest rate. At 11 AM of some imaginary day the stock rise and the "top story is":&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Stocks rise due to strong economic data

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Nice. A hour later, the stocks lose height, the "top story" says:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Stocks dip into the red as investors are concerned that the strong economic data will lead to a rise in the interest rates soon.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I kid you not - a hour later as the stocks emerge into the green again, the "top story" goes back to the first excuse. Geez... Just today, before the marked opened the "top story" babbled that US' good employment data in May can harm the stock market because "the interest rates will raise". When the marked opened with +1.0% on the Nasdaq, the "top story" now says:
U.S. stocks rose Friday following a strong May jobs report 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I can bet you a nickel that if the stocks end red today, we'll see again "concern of interest rates".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I just have the impression that these CBS MarketWatch dudes have seated some moron-head in the office, whose only job is to write such "stock commentaries" and "explain" them as well as possible (all "stories" are in past tense for some reason). It's no wonder the public treats economists with such suspicion - these people excel at predicting the past, and making mistakes about the future.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Argh.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Finance"></category><category term="Internet"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Free to choose" by Milton and Rose Friedman</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/04/27/book-review-free-to-choose-by-milton-and-rose-friedman" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-04-27T00:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-04-27:/2004/04/27/book-review-free-to-choose-by-milton-and-rose-friedman</id><summary type="html">
        Continuing with my financial education, I picked up this book in a store on sale - a Hebrew translation.&lt;p&gt;
Let me start by saying that this is the worse piece of editing/publication I've ever seen. The font is ugly, the paragraphs are scattered without the least care for aesthetics, and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        Continuing with my financial education, I picked up this book in a store on sale - a Hebrew translation.&lt;p&gt;
Let me start by saying that this is the worse piece of editing/publication I've ever seen. The font is ugly, the paragraphs are scattered without the least care for aesthetics, and the spelling errors... oh the spelling errors. FFS, the book was written in 1979, couldn't they release a normal Hebrew translation since then ? The errors look like scanning errors - letters replaced by letters that look like them. I bet no quality control was present in this printing house - the errors are so obvious...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Ok, ok, enough whining - lets cut to the chase. The book, as its title suggests, is about free economy. Milton Friedman is a known economics prof that holds some very interesting (and somewhat controversial) ideas about the economic market. His basic argument is that everything should be free - he relays on Adam Smith's "The wealth of nations" (I must read this book...), quoting the great economist about the merits of free trade.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Friedman attacks socialism and bureaucracy, and I don't mean the socialism in the USSR (the book was written in 1979...) but the socialism in the western world - US, England, etc. He argues that the govermental control of economics and business is too vast, which brings to a lot of waste, bureaucracy and generally slows down the economic progress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In fact - this is what this book is mostly about. The author discusses freedom against govermental control in business, monetary markets, education, health, energy, oil, trains, flights... everything. This is, I guess, why some think he's controversial. Some of his ideas are on the verge of anarchy - even I'll have to admit this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The general idea is sound - economy should be free, only from a free trade between people where each side is interesting in maximizing his own profit, a healthy economy will rise. Govermental control has historically proved to only slow things down and cause a lot of waste by means of feeding a huge bureaucratic machine. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The applications to finance, trade and historical examples are what I really loved in this book. It gave me a lot of food for thought, and helped me to reach a few interesting conclusions about economy. Pity that most of the book deals with the author's personal vendetta against the US goverment - trying to convince the reader how it got it all wrong, starting with Social Security and ending with the Drugs administration. It really started to get boring, and in the end I found myself just flippling through, seeking something new.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
To conclude this (as usual) scattered lump of thoughts I call a "book review" - this book has some good sides, but also some bad sides (IMHO, of course). I'm glad I've read it. From the fraction of it I actually enjoyed, I learned things that will help me shape my thoughts about economics and finance, and that's a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry><entry><title>outsourcing is good - a thought experiment</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/04/02/outsourcing-is-good-a-thought-experiment" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-04-02T12:44:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-04-02:/2004/04/02/outsourcing-is-good-a-thought-experiment</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
The more I read about economics, the more convinced I become that
outsourcing/offshoring is a good, natural thing (I wrote about this before in
this journal)...
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Consider a thought experiment: new tools are developed that boost productivity
of developers so much that 30% less developers are actually needed (This …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
The more I read about economics, the more convinced I become that
outsourcing/offshoring is a good, natural thing (I wrote about this before in
this journal)...
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Consider a thought experiment: new tools are developed that boost productivity
of developers so much that 30% less developers are actually needed (This is not
too far fetched, I think). What will happen ? Well, what happened when machines
replaced 100,000s of textile workers, what happened when factory automation
caused massive lay-offs ? How many secretaries/assistants/typers lost jobs as a
result of the PC ? The same will happen here, fewer developers will be needed,
so fewer will be employed. This is the free market economics, this is how these
things work.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Now, consider that this new tool was invented - it's called CIRR (China, India,
Russia, Romania). This tool allows companies to develop applications and do IT
with less cost than they currently do. We (thankfully) are part of a free
economic market, so companies naturally seek ways to do stuff cheaper.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Goverment invervention is wrong in such cases, as history proved more than once.
It's like fighting a new automated tools, like making laws that factories will
produce cars with 200 workers hand-crafting each part, instead of using
robots.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
More thoughts on this later...
&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Finance"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry><entry><title>story with a moral for stock trading</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/03/05/story-with-a-moral-for-stock-trading" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-03-05T17:10:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-03-05:/2004/03/05/story-with-a-moral-for-stock-trading</id><summary type="html">
        I have many unusual thoughts about trading stocks, and this story just hit the right cord with me:&lt;p&gt; 
In some American Indian reservation, the natives asked their chief about the upcoming winter - will it be cold or mild. The chief had no idea, but to look knowledgeable he told them …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        I have many unusual thoughts about trading stocks, and this story just hit the right cord with me:&lt;p&gt; 
In some American Indian reservation, the natives asked their chief about the upcoming winter - will it be cold or mild. The chief had no idea, but to look knowledgeable he told them that the winter will be very cold, and they should hew and store as much wood as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Some time later, the chief felt uncomfortable about telling this to his people without knowing, and had doubts, so he called the meteorologic service. They told him that the winter will be cold, so he felt a little calmer and told his people to store even more wood for the cold winter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
A few weeks later he called the meteorologic service again and got the same answer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
When he called the third time and was told that the winter is going to be very cold, he asked the weather-man what data he relies on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
"But that's obvious" said the weather-man "the natives are cutting down trees like crazy !".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahh... so true, so true for the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Hidden order: Economics of Everyday Life" by David Friedman</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/02/19/book-review-hidden-order-by-david-friedman" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-02-19T16:57:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-02-19:/2004/02/19/book-review-hidden-order-by-david-friedman</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
The goal of this book is to explain everyday life in economic
terms. More specifically, in terms of "economic equilibrium",
proving that the society has organized itself into an efficient
economic state.
This subject interests me a lot, so I decided to buy and read the
book.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Generally, I was …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
The goal of this book is to explain everyday life in economic
terms. More specifically, in terms of "economic equilibrium",
proving that the society has organized itself into an efficient
economic state.
This subject interests me a lot, so I decided to buy and read the
book.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Generally, I was not dissapointed. Friedman (a physics Ph.D. turned into
an economist) uses deductive, yet entertaining and readable
approach to explain how various things in life can be explained
economically. Mostly finance-related stuff like prices,
taxes, tariffs, rent, currency rates, trade balances etc. but also
things like military tactics (based on game theory), organized
crime, children's behavior and even marriage.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The approach the book takes is a very nice one from an educational
point of view, in my opinion. The author first starts with trivial
examples - a simplyfied economic system. He explains how things
work under these restricted conditions, and then starts to expand
the scope to more complicated economies.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The treating of game theory is especially good, as it touches a
compelling subject in a very readable manner.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
One fact about the book I don't like, though. Friedman doesn't spend
enough time explaining the basics of economics he relies on. It's as
if he assumes some initial acquintance with economics - supply/demand
curves, for example. I think I understand more economics
than the average Joe, but I never learned it officially. Even if I
have an intuitive comprehension of what supply/demand curves are, it
still doesn't mean that I will immediately grasp why these curves
"shift", how their slopes are related, and what do the areas between
them (on the graph) mean. Maybe I just hoped for an easy book, one that
wouldn't require thorough analysis of the material. I think
that the author could, in any case, make the problem go away with
a 10-20 page explanation of the economics basics he uses, especially
the various tricks with supply/demand curves. In my opinion, it would
make it a far better book.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
To summarize, "The hidden order" is indeed recommended, but more for people who
already have some understanding of economics - ideally who took some
basic economics courses in Uni. Maybe I'll reread it some day after
I'll have a better grasp of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Beating the street" by Peter Lynch</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/10/17/book-review-beating-the-street-by-peter-lynch" rel="alternate"></link><published>2003-10-17T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2003-10-17:/2003/10/17/book-review-beating-the-street-by-peter-lynch</id><summary type="html">
        After a couple of general inspirational books by Kyosaki, it was time to read something more serious.&lt;p&gt;
Peter Lynch is a legendary investor on the Wall Street. He managed a multi-billion dollar mutual fund (Fidelity Magellan) for more than 10 years, and was highly successful in this task. After he …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        After a couple of general inspirational books by Kyosaki, it was time to read something more serious.&lt;p&gt;
Peter Lynch is a legendary investor on the Wall Street. He managed a multi-billion dollar mutual fund (Fidelity Magellan) for more than 10 years, and was highly successful in this task. After he retired from the fund, he gave stock advise to the Barron panel - his insights were very useful then too, and on paper gained much more yields than the S&amp;amp;P 500. So what is his secret ? That's what this book is about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This book caused a lot of hype, #1 national bestseller (you know, Lynch's name much larger than the book title on the cover). Besides it was Lynch's second book. I was afraid it's a hype-book, repeating the same catchy idea in different forms for 300 pages. So, the pleasant surprise is: the book is nothing like that. It's very much "down to earth", with many advices that seem very practical.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Lynch admits that there's no magic in stock-picking, but it's mostly hard work. To have the good performance he had, Lynch worked 80 hour weeks, on weekends and on vacations. This is sobering. On one hand, you find out that picking good stock really IS hard (hopefully this doesn't surprise anyone). On the other hand, though, you see that although it's hard, it's not magical, it's a job like any other thought-demanding job. Think, learn, research, work and you will suceed. This, in fact, is the main message "Beating the street" is trying to pass on to its readers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
So what it takes to pick stocks, according to Lynch ? Looking at the charts and sensing "directions of the stock" is far from enough. One should learn to read financial statements of firms, to research the industry in which the firm operates, to feel and understand the trends in this industry. Picking a stock is a result of a lot of work. You buy a stock when you feel the company will rise, period. But deciding whether it will rise is a conglomeration of many factors, which Lynch tries to teach the readers.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
By all means, read the book if you plan to invest in the stock marked (be it through stocks, options or funds).&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry></feed>