<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Eli Bendersky's website - Miscellanea</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/feeds/miscellanea.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://eli.thegreenplace.net/</id><updated>2024-05-04T19:46:23-07:00</updated><entry><title>Enhorabuena a España</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2010/07/12/enhorabuena-a-espana" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-07-12T15:42:11-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2010-07-12:/2010/07/12/enhorabuena-a-espana</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
It was a tough game against Holland's karate^H^H^H^H^H... err, football team,
but Spain deserved to win.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Earlier this year my brother and I went to Barcelona where we saw this in the
window of some bank:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2010/07/espana_deposito_2010.jpg" title="espana_deposito_2010" width="440" height="582" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2245" /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

It says that it will provide a 3% yearly …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
It was a tough game against Holland's karate^H^H^H^H^H... err, football team,
but Spain deserved to win.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Earlier this year my brother and I went to Barcelona where we saw this in the
window of some bank:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2010/07/espana_deposito_2010.jpg" title="espana_deposito_2010" width="440" height="582" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2245" /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

It says that it will provide a 3% yearly revenue on some kind of long-term
deposit, and will increase the revenue to 4% if Spain gains the world cup. This
is what sports fanaticism looks like!
&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry><entry><title>Sad, but just</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2010/06/24/sad-but-just" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-06-24T18:19:38-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2010-06-24:/2010/06/24/sad-but-just</id><content type="html">
        &lt;img class="align-center" src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2010/06/200px-Flag_of_Italy.svg_.png" title="200px-Flag_of_Italy.svg" width="200" height="133" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2221" /&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;Squadra Azzurra, I love you, but you deserved it. There's no one else to blame. In the last 15 minutes of this game we finally saw a real football team wearing blue, but it was too little, too late.
        &lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry><entry><title>My articles published in a book!</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2009/04/28/my-articles-published-in-a-book" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-04-28T12:27:31-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-04T19:46:23-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2009-04-28:/2009/04/28/my-articles-published-in-a-book</id><summary type="html">
        A &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/03/08/my-articles-published-at-gamedev/"&gt;few years ago&lt;/a&gt; I've written several programming articles for the &lt;a href="http://www.gamedev.net/"&gt;GameDev online community website&lt;/a&gt;. The full list of articles is &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/tag/articles/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.

Well, a couple of months ago I was contacted by some guys from GameDev who planned to release a series of books collecting the most notable articles from …</summary><content type="html">
        A &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/03/08/my-articles-published-at-gamedev/"&gt;few years ago&lt;/a&gt; I've written several programming articles for the &lt;a href="http://www.gamedev.net/"&gt;GameDev online community website&lt;/a&gt;. The full list of articles is &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/tag/articles/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.

Well, a couple of months ago I was contacted by some guys from GameDev who planned to release a series of books collecting the most notable articles from the website into related chunks, editing them and adding some new material. My articles made it into the "Advanced Game Programming" book. The book (ISBN-10: 1598638068) was published last month.

So this is a first book publication for me! Although I made practically no money from it ($50 for each of my 3 chapters, without sale royalties), it does give me some bragging rights :-)

&lt;p&gt;Here's a shot from the book's table of contents, showing two of my chapters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class="align-center" src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2009/04/gamedev_book_toc.png" title="GameDev book table of contents" width="392" height="482" class="size-full wp-image-1670" /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the code accompanying chapter 6 has not been published with the book, so I've collected it together and placed it 
 &lt;a href="https://github.com/eliben/code-for-blog/tree/main/2009/regex_fsm"&gt;online here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry><entry><title>Productivity insights from "Getting things done"</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2008/06/20/productivity-insigths-from-getting-things-done" rel="alternate"></link><published>2008-06-20T07:36:10-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T13:41:52-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2008-06-20:/2008/06/20/productivity-insigths-from-getting-things-done</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
I've read David Allen's "Getting things done" &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/07/08/book-review-getting-things-done-by-david-allen/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, and yesterday I wanted to refresh my memory regarding the productivity tips it offers. 
      &lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;
So I skimmed through the book for a couple of hours. I think that I'm better at organization than I was in the past, so most of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
I've read David Allen's "Getting things done" &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/07/08/book-review-getting-things-done-by-david-allen/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, and yesterday I wanted to refresh my memory regarding the productivity tips it offers. 
      &lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;
So I skimmed through the book for a couple of hours. I think that I'm better at organization than I was in the past, so most of the tips in the book were quite obvious. However, I still gleaned a few interesting insights I want to file here for future review:
      &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tasks stay on your mind and make you worry mainly because they're unclear. Replace vague topics by concrete goals that can be acted upon. For example, if a part of your todo list now looks like:
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Foo&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Bar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Replace it by:
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Talk to Joe about implementing Foo&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Bar: read about super Widgets&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Bar: implement a mega Widget for patch 12&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Bar: do a code review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Some relevant quotes: &lt;em&gt;"This constant, unproductive preoccupation with all the things we have to do is the single largest consumer of time and energy"&lt;/em&gt;. and &lt;em&gt;"It is easier to act yourself into a better way of feeling than to feel yourself into a better way of action"&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You should periodically sort and empty your master to-do list. Emptying it doesn't necessarily mean doing everything on it. Rather, all the items on the list have to be assorted to more specific locations, like a calendar, per-project to-do lists and so on. Keeping a lot of stuff on the master list for long periods of time is counterproductive.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Weekly reviews of your tasks and goals are very important. No matter how well we try to organize ourselves, work often gets too hectic to follow a clearly defined plan all the time. A weekly review is a method to keep it all under control in the long run. Once a week, take some time to review all your pending tasks and to-do lists and set up more concrete goals for the week to come.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;


    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry><entry><title>A speeding ticket comes from afar</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/04/04/a-speeding-ticket-comes-from-afar" rel="alternate"></link><published>2007-04-04T18:09:02-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-21T13:10:55-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2007-04-04:/2007/04/04/a-speeding-ticket-comes-from-afar</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
Today I received a speeding ticket by mail. Posted by the police. The police of
New Zealand!
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

This is the first speed ticket in my life.
Thankfully only $80 NZD (about 250 NIS) - in Israel
they charge much more for speeding. Apparently I was driving at 111 kmh on
interstate …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
Today I received a speeding ticket by mail. Posted by the police. The police of
New Zealand!
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

This is the first speed ticket in my life.
Thankfully only $80 NZD (about 250 NIS) - in Israel
they charge much more for speeding. Apparently I was driving at 111 kmh on
interstate 6 (100 allowed) somewhere between Te Anau and Wanaka (South Island)
on February 5th. It doesn't surprise me really, since 110 is about the average
speed of our driving in NZ - everyone goes (at least) 110 there.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Oh well, there's a first time for everything I guess.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category><category term="Travel"></category></entry><entry><title>million, billion, milliard</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/07/12/million-billion-milliard" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-07-12T22:46:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-07-12:/2005/07/12/million-billion-milliard</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;A curious fact: how much "billion" is depends on where you live, and what language you speak.
&lt;p&gt;
In the American system, a billion is 1,000 millions, that is 10e9. In the British system, it's 10e12 (million millions). 10e12 is "trillion" in the American system - but hold on, it's 10e18 …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;A curious fact: how much "billion" is depends on where you live, and what language you speak.
&lt;p&gt;
In the American system, a billion is 1,000 millions, that is 10e9. In the British system, it's 10e12 (million millions). 10e12 is "trillion" in the American system - but hold on, it's 10e18 in the British system. 10e18 in American is "quintillion" but 10e30 in British.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, in Spanish a billón follows the British system: 10e12. An "American" billion in Spanish is "mil millones" - literally "a thousand millions".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To make things more interesting, there's another name for 10e9 - the "milliard". It's only rarely used in English, but is routinely used in Russian and Hebrew to describe 10e9. In fact, neither in Russian nor in Hebrew the word "billion" is used at all. "Trillion" in Russian and Hebrew follows the American system - 10e12&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry><entry><title>china, pebble bed nuclear reactors and hydrogen</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/07/03/china-pebble-bed-nuclear-reactors-and-hydrogen" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-07-03T21:09:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-07-03:/2005/07/03/china-pebble-bed-nuclear-reactors-and-hydrogen</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;A very interesting Wired article &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/12.09/china.html?pg=1&amp;amp;topic=china&amp;amp;topic_set=" rel="nofollow"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; about efforts of Chinise scientists and industries to open pebble-bed nuclear reactors for massive use.
&lt;p&gt;
Nuclear reactors have long been known to provide one of the most environmentally friendly power source, and surely the most powerful one. Their problem is safety (think three mile …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;A very interesting Wired article &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/12.09/china.html?pg=1&amp;amp;topic=china&amp;amp;topic_set=" rel="nofollow"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; about efforts of Chinise scientists and industries to open pebble-bed nuclear reactors for massive use.
&lt;p&gt;
Nuclear reactors have long been known to provide one of the most environmentally friendly power source, and surely the most powerful one. Their problem is safety (think three mile island, or Chernobyl).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The pebble-bed nuclear reactor design is different. It is inherently safe - its safety governed by physical laws. If you turn off all safety gear of such a reactor and send the operators home for supper, nothing will happen. The physical properties of the design impose a negative feedback that causes the reactor to cool off once it reaches a certain non-critical temperature. More about this &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pebble_bed_reactor" rel="nofollow"&gt;on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moreover, such a reactor can be used to efficiently generate hydrogen - which will provide ample fuel for fuel-cell powered vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
China plans on deploying 30 such plants by 2020 (the first will begin construction next year). I think it's great, perhaps from here will the freedom from oil come ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Curious that such advances come from China. It is a huge country with a lot of bright people, and it has immense needs for power and other resources. Smart people + demand fuels scientific advance.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category><category term="Science"></category></entry><entry><title>lost "lost"</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/06/10/lost-lost" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-06-10T10:09:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-06-10:/2005/06/10/lost-lost</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;How big was my dissapointment after finishing watching the last episode of "Lost" upon finding out that this dumb series hasn't ended.
&lt;p&gt;
Where do I even get started ? "Lost" is terrible - it's unrealistic, inconsistent, fakely-dramatic, politically correct and what not. A crash on a mysterious island is just an excuse …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;How big was my dissapointment after finishing watching the last episode of "Lost" upon finding out that this dumb series hasn't ended.
&lt;p&gt;
Where do I even get started ? "Lost" is terrible - it's unrealistic, inconsistent, fakely-dramatic, politically correct and what not. A crash on a mysterious island is just an excuse to show how f*cked up the lives of some people are. Every one has a life of a tele-novel, no less. No one normal... The dramas it tries to create are so obviously fake, they're funny, and the shallow &amp; inconsistent interaction between the people on the island only make everything worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A reasonable acting is the only shining light in this terrible creation. And to name the last 3 chapters "Exodus" (a obviously "endish" name) and still not end it - argh.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry><entry><title>random: elevators, vacum cleaners, books</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/05/04/random-elevators-vacum-cleaners-books" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-05-04T10:04:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-05-04:/2005/05/04/random-elevators-vacum-cleaners-books</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Found a news-note about a &lt;a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.daytonaelevator.com/Pneumatic%20Vacuum%20Elevator%20Main%20Page.htm"&gt;pneumatic air-driven elevator&lt;/a&gt;. Looks like a great idea, really. It seems so simple, hence the geniality. If I think of an elevator these days - it's a mess of cords, weights, steel rods and engines. The pneumatic elevator looks like a toy in comparison, but it …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Found a news-note about a &lt;a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.daytonaelevator.com/Pneumatic%20Vacuum%20Elevator%20Main%20Page.htm"&gt;pneumatic air-driven elevator&lt;/a&gt;. Looks like a great idea, really. It seems so simple, hence the geniality. If I think of an elevator these days - it's a mess of cords, weights, steel rods and engines. The pneumatic elevator looks like a toy in comparison, but it works ! A nice solution for people's homes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Speaking of sucked-in air... Our vacuum cleaner died, and trying to show I'm worth my EE degree, armed with a small multi-meter, a few screwdrivers, a rubber hand-glove and a flashlight I disassembled it to "debug" the problem. I managed to bring the engine to life for a few seconds, twice (by doing a "vacuum-cleaner CPR") but it seems burned and not wanting to function... Ah, so we have to buy a new one.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I have books flowing to me from many sources now - yay ! A few unread books on the shelf, a few in my Palm, two coming from Russia, two from a friend in Canada, two from O'Reilly for a review. Happy happy...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry><entry><title>random call for help, disabled users</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/04/17/random-call-for-help-disabled-users" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-04-17T23:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-04-17:/2005/04/17/random-call-for-help-disabled-users</id><summary type="html">
        Two interesting programming/human related things happened yesterday:
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I got an email from some Natural Languages graduate student asking me to code a small program for him. He said he found me through my website which features a lot of programming stuff, so he figured I know my way around …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        Two interesting programming/human related things happened yesterday:
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I got an email from some Natural Languages graduate student asking me to code a small program for him. He said he found me through my website which features a lot of programming stuff, so he figured I know my way around code and can do it for him, as a favor.Now, it's not the first time I get such requests, and my usual answer is "my hourly rate is ...", but it was a clear Saturday morning, the sun was shining and I felt generous. Besides, the program was trivial (generate random sentences built from 1-4 parts taken from text files). So, 10 minutes later I sent him the (Perl) code, adding a short paragraph on how to download ActivePerl and run it.

He replied with a big thank you - it was quite nice doing a favor to just some random person...&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I found out that one of the users of my ESMS program is blind. The admin of the league he plays in told me that the guy is using a text-to-speech synthesis tool to prepare his sheets and "read" match reports. He says that ESMS' being text-based is a big help for him, since he can not enjoy graphical interfaces.This really feels nice. Helping disabled people is exciting for me, I contacted the admin, asking him to find out from the user how I can help him even more, with special tweaks so that his life with ESMS will be even more pleasant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Miscellanea"></category></entry></feed>