<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Eli Bendersky's website - Personal</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://eli.thegreenplace.net/</id><updated>2023-05-09T03:06:22-07:00</updated><entry><title>Twenty years of blogging</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/twenty-years-of-blogging/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-08T20:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-09T03:06:22-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2023-05-08:/2023/twenty-years-of-blogging/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog has now been running for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/06/why-start-a-weblog"&gt;20 years!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty years... a significant chunk of a human's adult life; while so
many things in my life have changed since May 2003, the blog has remained a
constant companion. This milestone inspired me to do some archaeology using the
amazing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://archive.org/web/"&gt;Wayback …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog has now been running for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/06/why-start-a-weblog"&gt;20 years!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty years... a significant chunk of a human's adult life; while so
many things in my life have changed since May 2003, the blog has remained a
constant companion. This milestone inspired me to do some archaeology using the
amazing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://archive.org/web/"&gt;Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt;. It didn't have the very
first post, but I dug up one from just a week or so later - &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/13/book-review-the-designers-guide-to-vhdl-by-p-ashenden"&gt;a book review&lt;/a&gt;.
Here's how it looked on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://use.perl.org/~spur/journal/"&gt;http://use.perl.org/~spur/journal/&lt;/a&gt; (this link is long
dead, of course) in May 2003:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="How this blog looked twenty years ago" class="align-center" src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2023/blog-twenty-years-ago.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I wrote an update at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/05/06/ten-years-of-blogging"&gt;10 year mark&lt;/a&gt;, the blog
looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="How this blog looked ten years ago" class="align-center" src="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2023/blog-ten-years-ago.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The looks - along with the hosting and the software used to generate and run the
blog - changed in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/blogging-setup-with-pelican/"&gt;September 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and the
blog has had roughly the current format ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've made some adjustments to the infrastructure - comments outgrew their
usefulness and were &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2018/turning-off-blog-comments/"&gt;turned off in 2018&lt;/a&gt;.
To further reduce dependencies on
third-party services and make the blog faster and more self-contained,
blog analytics were switched to use a lightweight self-hosted solution &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2023/using-goatcounter-for-blog-analytics/"&gt;earlier
this year&lt;/a&gt;.
Some infrastructure changes and upgrades have been happening once in a while,
but these are completely transparent for readers. Otherwise, it's been going
pretty steady.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Downtime has been exceedingly rare, and the blog's serving of static HTML
proved to be robust and resilient to spikes - including &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; HN storms and
&amp;quot;hug of death&amp;quot; attempts. This is a great improvement from the previous
Wordpress-on-BlueHost approach, which struggled with uptime, especially in times
of load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blog has been averaging ~25 posts per year in the past 10 years, with
something like 100,000 monthly visits. The content has shifted with
my interests, from a focus on C++ and Python to more Go content with a mix of
Rust and other new technologies like WebAssembly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As before, big thanks to all my dedicated readers. Reader feedback has always
been a highlight of the blogging experience. I have no intention of stopping,
but can this blog &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; reach its 30th birthday? Only the future will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>In defense of books</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2022/in-defense-of-books/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-17T09:27:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2022-01-17:/2022/in-defense-of-books/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I'm asked &amp;quot;what podcasts do you listen to?&amp;quot;, after an uncomfortable pause
I'm forced to answer that &amp;quot;I usually don't&amp;quot;. The full explanation is almost
always too long for a brief friendly chat, but I did manage to articulate it to
friends a couple of times in recent history …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I'm asked &amp;quot;what podcasts do you listen to?&amp;quot;, after an uncomfortable pause
I'm forced to answer that &amp;quot;I usually don't&amp;quot;. The full explanation is almost
always too long for a brief friendly chat, but I did manage to articulate it to
friends a couple of times in recent history; I think it's time to put it down in
writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, I prefer &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.slow-media.net/manifesto"&gt;Slow Media&lt;/a&gt;,
and the slower the better. This means I'd rather read books than articles, blog
posts and video talks; I'd rather listen to audiobooks than to podcasts. The
same applies further down the scale; I prefer articles and blog posts to social
media, and if I do listen to a podcast I favor the long-form ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Wouldn't one learn more by spending 10 hours listening to 10-20 podcasts
on different topics than by spending the same time on a single book?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this question is phrased in a suggestive way, I posit that the answer - at
least for me - is actually &lt;strong&gt;NO&lt;/strong&gt;, at least when viewed strategically rather
than tactically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consuming information is a marathon, not a sprint. It's not the case that I have
10 hours allocated in my life to consume information and I have to be as
efficient as possible; the truth is that over the years, I have many thousands
of hours. While it may appear that given 10 hours listening to the more
condensed podcast format is more efficient, the same is absolutely not apparent
if the decision is between 1000 books and 15,000 podcast episodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose I'm interested in 20 different topics. I could read two books on each
topic - 40 books in total; at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2020/my-reading-habits/"&gt;my current pace of reading&lt;/a&gt; this would probably
take a bit less than a year. Alternatively, I could spend these ~400 hours
listening to podcasts and/or reading articles on the same 20 topics. It's
slicing the same cake of time, just along different axes.
One could claim that with articles and podcasts you could learn about more than
20 topics in a given year, but do you really want to? I'd say even 20 is a
stretch, at least if by &amp;quot;learn&amp;quot; you mean at least some minimal depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In programming terms, it's a bit like using DFS vs. BFS to explore the same
knowledge graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the actual information intake is similar with the two approaches over a long
time period, why prefer one over the other? This is where the quality and depth
of information comes in. Books typically win on depth, since authors have put
much more effort into researching and writing them than is put into podcasts or
articles. Books also win on quality because they are easier to vet; when I plan
to spend 10 hours on reading a book, I can afford spending 15 minutes on
researching &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; book to read, looking at reviews, looking at samples, etc.
When one plans to spend 45 minutes on a podcast episode, any non-trivial
investment into research seems wasteful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll end this post with a few disclaimers: none of this is a rigid rule. I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;
listen to podcasts every once in a while, and I do read articles and blogs
posts. Some of them are of a very high quality and informational value. I'll
also note that some podcasts are packaged in well-researched and in-depth
&lt;em&gt;series&lt;/em&gt;, which makes them very similar to books at this point. I'm not dogmatic
about these things; just stating my preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Reading"></category><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Ten years of blogging</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/05/06/ten-years-of-blogging" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-06T05:32:03-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T15:35:51-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2013-05-06:/2013/05/06/ten-years-of-blogging</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;It has occurred to me that the first post in this blog was &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/06/why-start-a-weblog/"&gt;10 years ago&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to dig up a bit of history. 10 years is a long time! As the post linked above shows, I even called it &amp;quot;weblog&amp;quot; then. The term &amp;quot;blog&amp;quot; seems to have …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;It has occurred to me that the first post in this blog was &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/05/06/why-start-a-weblog/"&gt;10 years ago&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to dig up a bit of history. 10 years is a long time! As the post linked above shows, I even called it &amp;quot;weblog&amp;quot; then. The term &amp;quot;blog&amp;quot; seems to have been coined in 1999, but probably wasn't popular enough in 2003 yet. That post also closes with a hope that the blog will last; it sure did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these 10 years the blog went from an obscure journal on use.perl.org that
only a few people knew about to 66,000 unique visitors with half a million page
views a month on average (stats for end-of 2012).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it looks very different from the initial &amp;quot;weblog&amp;quot;, it actually went through relatively few incarnations for its age. Starting &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/09/02/becoming-unhappy-with-useperlorg/"&gt;somewhere in 2005&lt;/a&gt; I became unhappy with use.perl.org and eventually &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/03/28/my-transition-to-blogger-is-complete/"&gt;moved the blog to Blogger&lt;/a&gt;. But Blogger itself was quite limited for serious programming-related blogging at the time, so it took me only two weeks to figure out it's not quite what I wanted and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/04/12/migrating-to-wordpress/"&gt;move to a Wordpress-based blog&lt;/a&gt; on my own domain and shared hosting (Bluehost). In the seven years that has passed since, the blog changed very little visually. I stretched the main viewing area bit by bit as high-resolution monitors became more common, installed a couple of minor plugins, but that's it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did change was the quality of content. As I &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/01/06/this-blog-and-google-division-of-responsibilities/"&gt;wrote here&lt;/a&gt;, the blog became much more technical with time, leaving the shorter and more personal posts to outlets like G+. The amount of technical content is also the reason the blog's popularity grew rapidly in the past few years. Apparently more people want to know how debuggers work and about the internals of Python and Linux loaders than about some random cool library I found or how I spent the last week at work being bored. Go figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dedicated readers will notice that the number of in-depth posts has slowed down in the past few months. This was to be expected, having moved to a different continent and started a much more demanding job. But I still hope to continue posting articles from time to time. This blog is far from being done! As for infrastructure, I was actually pondering to make a large change after yet another &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/10/14/thinking-of-dumping-wordpress/"&gt;break-your-site Wordpress upgrade&lt;/a&gt;. But I still haven't found time to do this. Maybe at some point I will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So thanks for reading, and wishing myself at least another 10 years of blogging. It has been an incredibly positive experience for me in many respects, and I have full intention of keeping it up as long as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Why I may not be able to help you</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2013/02/06/why-i-may-not-be-able-to-help-you" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-02-06T06:05:46-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2013-02-06:/2013/02/06/why-i-may-not-be-able-to-help-you</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
Since this blog features a lot of programming content, I'm receiving quite a bit
of email from people asking for help and advice, either about something specific
I wrote, or just general questions. This isn't new - it's been going on for
years. But my attitude towards this has changed over …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
Since this blog features a lot of programming content, I'm receiving quite a bit
of email from people asking for help and advice, either about something specific
I wrote, or just general questions. This isn't new - it's been going on for
years. But my attitude towards this has changed over time. Some years ago, I was
almost always willing to help. It was an opportunity to learn, and I was very
proud that someone I haven't ever met seeks my advice just because I
wrote a blog post about this and that. These days, however, it's getting harder
and harder for me to find the time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You have to realize that the amount of time I have for these things is extremely
small. I have a full-time job I find challenging and interesting, and most of my
off-work time is spent with my family. In the scant weekly hours I have
remaining for "hobby programming", I'm hopelessly oversubscribed with taking
care of my active open-source projects, contributing to Python and writing new
articles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This doesn't mean you should not ask. If the question pertains to a project I
actively maintain, I will certainly answer. The issue tracker for that project
is the best place to ask though, not email. If it's about something I wrote
relatively recently in the blog - there's also a high chance of getting an
answer. If it's something I wrote a while ago, it depends on how much I'm still
interested in the subject, so I may not be able to provide a good answer. In
some extreme cases I may not answer an email at all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The chance of a question getting a good answer also depends on the question. If
it's a short question asking about something very specific, and requiring a
short answer, it has a higher chance of getting a good answer. If you're dumping
a 50-page spec on me asking "how to design this" (this happened so many times it
doesn't even surprise me any longer), then not so much.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's also the issue of consulting. In general, I very rarely accept
consulting gigs. Historically, I've been mainly doing this to compensate for a
certain lack of challenge and passion in my day job, and this is no longer an
issue. However, you may try. I've been known to take some consulting gigs of
varying lengths if the subject interested me enough. Folks have also paid me
just to have long and meaningful email conversations about subjects they
believed I'm knowledgeable in. So if you need help with a work project and are
willing to pay, you may approach me with a consulting proposal, but please state
it explicitly. The amount I've been charging recently is $150 per hour, but a
new quote may depend on the nature of the project.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To conclude, while I'm certainly happy to be receiving such emails and often can
provide the answers, this is not guaranteed. If you only get a polite "I can't
help" from me, don't take it personally. I'm just a regular person with limited
free time who has to carefully allocate what it's being used for.
&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Personal"></category><category term="Programming"></category></entry><entry><title>This blog is taking a short break</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/08/26/this-blog-is-taking-a-short-break" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-08-26T07:02:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2012-08-26:/2012/08/26/this-blog-is-taking-a-short-break</id><summary type="html">
        I haven't really had a vacation since my daughter was born almost two years ago. Well, now we'll be taking a big one :-)

In the next three weeks or so I'll be on a vacation. Afterwards, due to moving the family 12,000 km westwards and starting a new job …</summary><content type="html">
        I haven't really had a vacation since my daughter was born almost two years ago. Well, now we'll be taking a big one :-)

In the next three weeks or so I'll be on a vacation. Afterwards, due to moving the family 12,000 km westwards and starting a new job (Googleplex, here I come), I expect an additional downtime of at least a month or two, especially for the more in-depth articles in the blog.

But worry not, it will be back.
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>reading good books</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/07/25/reading-good-books" rel="alternate"></link><published>2003-07-25T13:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2003-07-25:/2003/07/25/reading-good-books</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
Some time ago I decided that if I read a lot of books (fiction), these should at
least be good ones. So, I found some page listing the 100 best books of the
19-20th centuries (according to polls from various newspapers). To my
astonishment, I've only read a handful from …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
Some time ago I decided that if I read a lot of books (fiction), these should at
least be good ones. So, I found some page listing the 100 best books of the
19-20th centuries (according to polls from various newspapers). To my
astonishment, I've only read a handful from that list. Here are the books I read
that are one the list, &lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;after&lt;/b&gt; I discovered the list:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orwell, George. Nineteen Eighty-Four  (&lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nabokov, Vladimir. Lolita (&lt;b&gt;after&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marquez, Gabriel Garcia. One Hundred Years of Solitude (&lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huxley, Aldous. Brave New World (&lt;b&gt;after&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twain, Mark. The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn (&lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wharton, Edith. The Age of Innocence (&lt;b&gt;after&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heller, Joseph. Catch-22 (&lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mitchell, Margaret. Gone With The Wind (&lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orwell, George. Animal Farm (&lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tolkien, J.R.R.. The Lord of the Rings (&lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tolstoy, Leo. War and Peace (&lt;b&gt;after&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carroll, Lewis. Alice's Adventures in Wonderland (&lt;b&gt;after&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burgess, Anthony. A Clockwork Orange (&lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Melville, Herman. Moby Dick (&lt;b&gt;after - in progress&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, as you see from the multitude of &lt;b&gt;after&lt;/b&gt;s, I'm making a good progress
in reading quality books. And I must say - these are quality books indeed, I
liked 90% of them...
&lt;/p&gt;

Moby Dick, as I mentioned, is in progress... but considering the length of the
book and the fact that I read 3-4 books in parallel, it may take some time.
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Personal"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry></feed>