<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Eli Bendersky's website - Philosophical</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/feeds/philosophical.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://eli.thegreenplace.net/</id><updated>2022-12-15T13:27:28-08:00</updated><entry><title>Asimov, programming and the meta ladder</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2022/asimov-programming-and-the-meta-ladder/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-22T17:02:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-12-15T13:27:28-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2022-01-22:/2022/asimov-programming-and-the-meta-ladder/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite stories by Isaac Asimov is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Profession_(novella)"&gt;Profession&lt;/a&gt;. The following is a
spoiler, so please read the story before proceeding if you don't like spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the futuristic society of year 6000-something, people no longer need to learn
their profession from books, lectures or hands-on experience. Each person …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite stories by Isaac Asimov is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Profession_(novella)"&gt;Profession&lt;/a&gt;. The following is a
spoiler, so please read the story before proceeding if you don't like spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the futuristic society of year 6000-something, people no longer need to learn
their profession from books, lectures or hands-on experience. Each person has
their brain analyzed at a certain age and then the know-how for the occupation
that's best suited for them is simply uploaded into the brain using special
cassettes (hey, this story is 60 years old) and electrodes. The folks who end up
the best at their craft (determined via competitions) end up with high-demand
assignments on &amp;quot;Class A&amp;quot; outer worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protagonist, George Platen, has a dream of getting &amp;quot;educated&amp;quot; in a certain
profession and reaching a desirable assignment. But he runs into trouble when
his brain assessment determines that no profession is a good fit for him, and
he's placed in a special &amp;quot;house for the feeble-minded&amp;quot; to spend his time however
he wants, even reading books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, after some adventures George discovers the truth on his own;
someone has to create these training cassettes, advance human technology and
update training materials to account for these advances. There's a
&amp;quot;meta-profession&amp;quot;, something akin to scientist, and George was selected for this
meta-profession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always loved this story for the meta aspect; many occupations are prone to
automation, and this has become much more true since Asimov first put the plot
to paper. But some human professions are necessarily &amp;quot;meta&amp;quot;; you can automate
them, but this just generates new professions that have to develop said
automation. Ad infinitum, or at least until &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_singularity"&gt;Singularity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of my career, I've heard the promises of &amp;quot;no code&amp;quot; programming
many times. These tools didn't cause the demand for programmers to plummet, but
to simply shift in other directions. More recently, I treat the hype about AI
coding assistants like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GitHub_Copilot"&gt;GitHub Copilot&lt;/a&gt; with similar calm. These are
great tools that are going to make some programmers' lives easier, but replace
programmers? Nope; only move programmers another notch up the meta ladder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, do you know what profession George Platen was aiming at before he
knew the truth? Computer programmer. A far-sighted move by Asimov, given that
the story was written in 1957!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Programming"></category><category term="Philosophical"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Discourse on the Method..." by René Descartes</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2008/10/28/book-review-discourse-on-the-method-by-rene-descartes" rel="alternate"></link><published>2008-10-28T20:18:22-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2008-10-28:/2008/10/28/book-review-discourse-on-the-method-by-rene-descartes</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
The full name of the book is: "Discourse on the Method of Rightly Conducting
One’s Reason and of Seeking Truth in the Sciences".
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Descartes is a very notable French philosopher that lived in the first part of
the 17th century. He's made huge contributions to both philosopy and
mathematics …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
The full name of the book is: "Discourse on the Method of Rightly Conducting
One’s Reason and of Seeking Truth in the Sciences".
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Descartes is a very notable French philosopher that lived in the first part of
the 17th century. He's made huge contributions to both philosopy and
mathematics. In philosophy, he laid down the foundations of rationalism, and
thus is considered one of the fathers of modern philosophy. In mathematics, he
discovered analytical geometry, the Cartesian coordinate system, the law of
conservation of momentum and made substantial progress in optics and the early
foundations of calculus.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The "Discourse on the Method" is the first philosophical work Descartes has
published, at the age of 41 (although he's apparently completed it much
earlier). It's a rather small book that takes a couple of hours to read, which
makes its importance and fame even more remarkable.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Part 1 serves as an introduction. Descartes presents himself as having "an
average mind". In spite of this, he is clearly happy with choosing a path in
life that directs him to pursuit knowledge and self improvement:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I will not hesitate, however, to avow my belief that it has been my singular good  fortune to have very early in life fallen in with certain tracks which have conducted me to considerations and maxims, of which I have formed a method that gives me the means, as I think, of gradually augmenting my knowledge, and of raising it by little and little to the highest point which the mediocrity of my talents and the brief duration of my life will permit me to reach.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
He provides an auto-biographic background, telling about his early life of
"reading the letters" (writings by scientists and philosophers of the past).
Left utterly unsatisfied with the answers he's found in these books, he decided
to engage on a different path for obtaining knowledge and understanding of the
world, and spent a few years traveling around Europe, "learning the customs and
conversing with different people".
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
It is useful to know something of the manners of different nations, that we may
be enabled to form a more correct judgment regarding our own, and be prevented
from thinking that everything contrary to our customs is ridiculous and
irrational, a conclusion usually come to by those whose experience has been
limited to their own country.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Especially, he was dissapointed with the readings of philosophy:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Of philosophy I will say nothing, except that when I saw that it had been cultivated for many ages by the most distinguished men, and that yet there is not a single matter within its sphere which is not still in dispute, and nothing, therefore, which is above doubt&lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Part 2 begins by a long metaphor that Descartes uses to explain how he planned
to overthrow the knowledge he gained from the books and replace it with a fuller
understanding of the world, collected from his travels and reflections.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

He eventually comes to one of the most famous parts of the book, "The Method",
which consists of 4 parts:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The first was never to accept anything for true which I did not clearly know to be such; that is to say, carefully to avoid precipitancy and prejudice, and to comprise nothing more in my judgement than what was presented to my mind so clearly and distinctly as to exclude all ground of doubt. 
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The second, to divide each of the difficulties under examination into as many
parts as possible, and as might be necessary for its adequate solution. 
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The third, to conduct my thoughts in such order that, by commencing with objects
the simplest and easiest to know, I might ascend by little and little, and, as
it were, step by step, to the knowledge of the more complex; assigning in
thought a certain order even to those objects which in their own nature do not
stand in a relation of antecedence and sequence. 
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

And the last, in every case to make enumerations so complete, and reviews so
general, that I might be assured that nothing was omitted. &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Note that it is an early exposition of the "problem solving" methods so
celebrated today by authors that manage to write whole books with less substance
than contained in the quote above.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Descartes then notes that an accurate observance of these rules enabled him to
solve a few interesting scientific problems. Indeed, one of his examples of the
application of "The Method" appeared in the appendix of the book and served as a
basis for calculus.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Descartes begins Part 3 with another list, a "code of morals" which he set for
himself to live by "in the mean time", while he's using the method to think of a
new approach for life. In short, he avows to: 
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Obey the laws and customs of his country, and try to behave according to "the most moderate opinions, and the farthest removed from the extremes". This is one of many places in the book in which Descartes expresses his carefulness of surfacing new and radical ideas. It makes a lot of sense if you consider the period in which he lived, when the church ruled and opposed all "new and radical" ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;To be firm and resolute in one's decisions. Even if they've been decided under difficult conditions with lots of unknowns - once the decision is made, stick to it.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;To conquer oneself by adopting the desires to the world rather than wishing it to be the other way. Note how similar this is to Ayn Rand's first principle of metaphysics. Descartes laid the foundation of rational thinking upon which lays a whole philosphic framework of many centuries forward.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;He decided to review all the "different occupations of men in this life, with the view of making choice of the best". In this quest Descartes reached the conclusion that &lt;em&gt;I could not do better than continue in that in which I was engaged, viz., in devoting my whole life to the culture of my reason, and in making the greatest progress I was able in the knowledge of truth, on the principles of the method which I had prescribed to myself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

Part 4 has several interesting points. It begins with the famous:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I observed that, whilst I thus wished to think that all was false, it was absolutely necessary that I, who thus thought, should be somewhat; and as I observed that this truth, &lt;em&gt;I think, therefore I am (COGITO ERGO SUM)&lt;/em&gt;, was so certain and of such evidence that no ground of doubt, however extravagant, could be alleged by the sceptics capable of shaking it, I concluded that I might, without scruple, accept it as the first principle of the philosophy of which I was in search. &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

He also reasons about the separate existence of body and soul, reaching the
conclusion that the soul must exist and be immortal. Then, he uses the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ontological_argument"&gt;ontological
argument&lt;/a&gt; to "prove" that God exists, by claiming that the fact that he can
clearly perceive that he's not perfect, and can think of a more perfect being
than himself, it clearly must be God, because otherwise who could have implanted
in him this perception of perfection beyond his own ?
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Naturally, these days this argument sounds hardly convincing. But it makes sense
in the historical context Descartes lived in, when people were born and raised
into intense religion and were nurtured and schooled with a dogma that left no
doubt in their minds of the existence of God. Otherwise, it's difficult to see
how Descartes, who openly proclaimed the ability of his pure reason to perceive
this world could have so easily fallen to a deeply flawed argument that doesn't
make much sense from a rationalistic point of view.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Part 5 is mainly devoted to reasoning about the structure of our bodies, and of
the bodies of animals, whereby the author attempts to expound on the "clear"
separation of body and soul. He engages in a long and quite dull description of
how an animal heart works, after which he reaches the subject of how machines
could perhaps fake the functions of the body but in no way of the soul.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Amazing insight from Descartes, in the 17th century to presuppose the creation
of machines that can behave and talk like humans! Of course, his reasonings on
the innate difference in the souls of humans and animals have recently been
overthrown by experiments with apes that show intelligence and can converse with
people using specially designed sign languages and computers. But still, it can
be said with confidence that he conceived an equivalent of the Turing test of
intelligence, 400 years before Turing.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Part 6 was written 3 years after the others, and in it Descarts explains the
reasons that have prevented him from publishing the work. He speaks of "another
individual" who has published "a certain doctrine in physics" which didn't seem
controversial to Descartes but raised great opposition. I don't know if it's
related, but Galileo Galilei has published one of his first works in 1610 and
raised great controversy with the church. The times Galilei and Descartes lived
in were not good for scientific discoveries, and Descartes's caution can be
easily understood.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Nevertheless, he continues to raise many reasons &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; publishing The
Method, which he did indeed publish, eventually.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Well, it's time to conclude the review. I think that in order to be trury
appreciated, this book must be viewed in historic context. The ideas Descartes
present hardly catch anyone by surprise today, because they're mostly maxims
generally accepted today, at least amongst people of scientific inclination and
rationalists. But what's truly impressive is that his ideas are the basis of
these maxims, the foundations on which most of modern philosophy lays.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

So if you're looking for a book to expand your horizons, this hardly is it. But
if you're interested in the history of philosophy, or in turn, like me, seek to
start any path of learning from the basics, you probably won't be dissapointed
with spending 2-3 hours on reading this book.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Philosophical"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Capitalism, an unknown ideal" by Ayn Rand</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/07/21/book-review-capitalism-an-unknown-ideal-by-ayn-rand" rel="alternate"></link><published>2006-07-21T15:54:09-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2006-07-21:/2006/07/21/book-review-capitalism-an-unknown-ideal-by-ayn-rand</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
Capitalism as a political system is one of the corner-stones of Ayn Rand's
philosophy, and this book is an extensive collection of articles and essays by
Rand and other well-known proponents of her views (Nathaniel Branden and Alan
Greenspan, to name a couple). 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Amidst some interesting and insightful essays on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
Capitalism as a political system is one of the corner-stones of Ayn Rand's
philosophy, and this book is an extensive collection of articles and essays by
Rand and other well-known proponents of her views (Nathaniel Branden and Alan
Greenspan, to name a couple). 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Amidst some interesting and insightful essays on the topics of capitalism, man's
rights, and goverment's role in everyday life, there are some articles which are
hard to read and understand, mostly because today they read "out of context":
Many articles in this book were collected from the "Objectivist newsletter" (a
publication dedicated to Objectivisim) during the 1960s. They mostly deal with
issues which were "hot" back then - political turbulences in universities,
opposition to the war in Vietnam, and so on. It's hard to relate to these
articles now in 2006.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I'm not one to be convinced that laissez-faire (which means "leave us alone" in
French, by the way) is the way to go economic-policy wise, and yet I got this
book to try and understand capitalism in a deeper sense from Rand's point of
view. Having finished it without gaining much new information, it dawned on me
that this in itself is the answer - capitalism is simple, basic, natural. It's
so simple that it takes one catch-phrase to understand (laissez faire !), it
really does boil down to "leave us alone and let us trade as we see fit".
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I think I probably need to read more on the topic though, preferably some
non-fiction works comparing capitalism and the various forms of socialism /
monarchy as alternative political systems from a historical point of view.
&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Philosophical"></category></entry><entry><title>a summary of Ayn Rand's philosophy</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/05/23/a-summary-of-ayn-rands-philosophy" rel="alternate"></link><published>2006-05-23T18:17:26-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2006-05-23:/2006/05/23/a-summary-of-ayn-rands-philosophy</id><summary type="html">
        I want to archive for myself the following short essay by Ayn Rand, taken from &lt;a href="http://www.aynrand.org/site/PageServer?pagename=objectivism_intro"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is Ayn Rand's reply when asked to "present the essence of her philosophy while standing on one foot":

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
1. Metaphysics: Objective Reality
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
2. Epistemology: Reason
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
3. Ethics: Self-interest
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
4. Politics: Capitalism
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

If you …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        I want to archive for myself the following short essay by Ayn Rand, taken from &lt;a href="http://www.aynrand.org/site/PageServer?pagename=objectivism_intro"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is Ayn Rand's reply when asked to "present the essence of her philosophy while standing on one foot":

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
1. Metaphysics: Objective Reality
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
2. Epistemology: Reason
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
3. Ethics: Self-interest
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
4. Politics: Capitalism
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

If you want this translated into simple language, it would read: 1. "Nature, to
be commanded, must be obeyed" or "Wishing won't make it so." 2. "You can't eat
your cake and have it, too." 3. "Man is an end in himself." 4. "Give me liberty
or give me death."
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

If you held these concepts with total consistency, as the base of your
convictions, you would have a full philosophical system to guide the course of
your life. But to hold them with total consistency—to understand, to define, to
prove and to apply them—requires volumes of thought. Which is why philosophy
cannot be discussed while standing on one foot—nor while standing on two feet on
both sides of every fence. This last is the predominant philosophical position
today, particularly in the field of politics.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

My philosophy, Objectivism, holds that:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

   1. Reality exists as an objective absolute—facts are facts, independent of
   man's feelings, wishes, hopes or fears.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
   2. Reason (the faculty which identifies and integrates the material provided
   by man's senses) is man's only means of perceiving reality, his only source
   of knowledge, his only guide to action, and his basic means of survival.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
   3. Man—every man—is an end in himself, not the means to the ends of others.
   He must exist for his own sake, neither sacrificing himself to others nor
   sacrificing others to himself. The pursuit of his own rational self-interest
   and of his own happiness is the highest moral purpose of his life.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
   4. The ideal political-economic system is laissez-faire capitalism. It is a
   system where men deal with one another, not as victims and executioners, nor
   as masters and slaves, but as traders, by free, voluntary exchange to mutual
   benefit. It is a system where no man may obtain any values from others by
   resorting to physical force, and no man may initiate the use of physical
   force against others. The government acts only as a policeman that protects
   man's rights; it uses physical force only in retaliation and only against
   those who initiate its use, such as criminals or foreign invaders. In a
   system of full capitalism, there should be (but, historically, has not yet
   been) a complete separation of state and economics, in the same way and for
   the same reasons as the separation of state and church.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Philosophical"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review; "NLP: the new technology" by NLP Comprehensive</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/07/01/book-review-nlp-the-new-technology-by-nlp-comprehensive" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-07-01T11:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-07-01:/2005/07/01/book-review-nlp-the-new-technology-by-nlp-comprehensive</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Preamble: NLP stands for Neuro Linguistic Programming. It is a method to use imagination in order to affect the way your brain perceives things and thus alter your mood / state of mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This book aims to be "all of NLP squeezed in" and is certainly not for NLP beginners, like …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Preamble: NLP stands for Neuro Linguistic Programming. It is a method to use imagination in order to affect the way your brain perceives things and thus alter your mood / state of mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This book aims to be "all of NLP squeezed in" and is certainly not for NLP beginners, like me. If it's your first encounter with NLP, you won't learn much from it, as it doesn't explain the basics at all, but rather provides tons of exercises that can be done rightly only if you've already mastered the NLP techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me it read like an average self-help book, much inferior to others and rather shallow overall. I guess it should be the second NLP book for people, after they've mastered the basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, it does raise my interest in NLP, which seems to be a down to earth technique, explaning why it works in more-or-less scientific terms and not with "the infinite intelligence that governs the world...". Shortly, many books that speak about the subconscious mind are religious propagandas in disguise. NLP seems to be different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can't say I enjoyed this book... like any self-help book it has some nice points that are worth to remember. I guess I should learn more about the basics of NLP, and come back to the exercises / training program in this book later.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Philosophical"></category></entry></feed>