<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Eli Bendersky's website - Reading</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/feeds/reading.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://eli.thegreenplace.net/</id><updated>2024-05-04T16:00:57-07:00</updated><entry><title>In defense of books</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2022/in-defense-of-books/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-17T09:27:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2022-01-17:/2022/in-defense-of-books/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I'm asked &amp;quot;what podcasts do you listen to?&amp;quot;, after an uncomfortable pause
I'm forced to answer that &amp;quot;I usually don't&amp;quot;. The full explanation is almost
always too long for a brief friendly chat, but I did manage to articulate it to
friends a couple of times in recent history …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I'm asked &amp;quot;what podcasts do you listen to?&amp;quot;, after an uncomfortable pause
I'm forced to answer that &amp;quot;I usually don't&amp;quot;. The full explanation is almost
always too long for a brief friendly chat, but I did manage to articulate it to
friends a couple of times in recent history; I think it's time to put it down in
writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, I prefer &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.slow-media.net/manifesto"&gt;Slow Media&lt;/a&gt;,
and the slower the better. This means I'd rather read books than articles, blog
posts and video talks; I'd rather listen to audiobooks than to podcasts. The
same applies further down the scale; I prefer articles and blog posts to social
media, and if I do listen to a podcast I favor the long-form ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Wouldn't one learn more by spending 10 hours listening to 10-20 podcasts
on different topics than by spending the same time on a single book?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this question is phrased in a suggestive way, I posit that the answer - at
least for me - is actually &lt;strong&gt;NO&lt;/strong&gt;, at least when viewed strategically rather
than tactically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consuming information is a marathon, not a sprint. It's not the case that I have
10 hours allocated in my life to consume information and I have to be as
efficient as possible; the truth is that over the years, I have many thousands
of hours. While it may appear that given 10 hours listening to the more
condensed podcast format is more efficient, the same is absolutely not apparent
if the decision is between 1000 books and 15,000 podcast episodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose I'm interested in 20 different topics. I could read two books on each
topic - 40 books in total; at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2020/my-reading-habits/"&gt;my current pace of reading&lt;/a&gt; this would probably
take a bit less than a year. Alternatively, I could spend these ~400 hours
listening to podcasts and/or reading articles on the same 20 topics. It's
slicing the same cake of time, just along different axes.
One could claim that with articles and podcasts you could learn about more than
20 topics in a given year, but do you really want to? I'd say even 20 is a
stretch, at least if by &amp;quot;learn&amp;quot; you mean at least some minimal depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In programming terms, it's a bit like using DFS vs. BFS to explore the same
knowledge graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the actual information intake is similar with the two approaches over a long
time period, why prefer one over the other? This is where the quality and depth
of information comes in. Books typically win on depth, since authors have put
much more effort into researching and writing them than is put into podcasts or
articles. Books also win on quality because they are easier to vet; when I plan
to spend 10 hours on reading a book, I can afford spending 15 minutes on
researching &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; book to read, looking at reviews, looking at samples, etc.
When one plans to spend 45 minutes on a podcast episode, any non-trivial
investment into research seems wasteful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll end this post with a few disclaimers: none of this is a rigid rule. I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;
listen to podcasts every once in a while, and I do read articles and blogs
posts. Some of them are of a very high quality and informational value. I'll
also note that some podcasts are packaged in well-researched and in-depth
&lt;em&gt;series&lt;/em&gt;, which makes them very similar to books at this point. I'm not dogmatic
about these things; just stating my preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Reading"></category><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>My Reading Habits</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2020/my-reading-habits/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-02T05:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-05-04T16:00:57-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2020-01-02:/2020/my-reading-habits/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2019 I've finished 63 books, which is a new personal record:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object class="align-center" data="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2020/chart-books-read.svg" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;Chart of books read yearly 2003-2019&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began keeping detailed track of my reading when this blog launched in 2003. In
case you're wondering, the total count since 2003 is just a bit over 700, though
this overcounts …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2019 I've finished 63 books, which is a new personal record:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object class="align-center" data="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/images/2020/chart-books-read.svg" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;Chart of books read yearly 2003-2019&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began keeping detailed track of my reading when this blog launched in 2003. In
case you're wondering, the total count since 2003 is just a bit over 700, though
this overcounts by 10-15% if we consider &lt;em&gt;unique&lt;/em&gt; books, since I re-read books
quite a bit (more on this later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seemed like a good time to reflect and also answer some frequently asked
questions I get from followers about my reading habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading books is an important part of my life. Reading a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; book is an
activity I enjoy on a profound level. It's not just for passing time; it's
for gaining a deeper understanding of the world we inhabit, and for shaping my
own view of myself and my place in this world. Therefore, the effort to find
good books to read is never-ending, and over the years my summaries have helped
many people fill up their own reading queues - very happy to help!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; questions from followers about my reading habits. Here's a bit of
Q&amp;amp;A. The first question is by far the most common, but others come up quite a
bit as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; How do you find time to read so much?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; I make time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's as simple as that. When people ask me this question, I always feel tempted
to ask back &amp;quot;Why do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; think &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; don't have time?&amp;quot;. I'm convinced
that anyone can find time if they really want it; it's just a matter of
priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel compelled to add that I don't see myself as any sort of record-breaking
reader. There are many people who read way more than me, both in terms of
quantity and quality. I still have much to learn about time management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more detailed answer is due, though. It's a combination of several factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Audiobooks: these make up a sizable chunk (at least a third) of my
reading in the past few years. I can carve up a lot of reading time while
commuting, working out, waiting at my kids' after-school activities, washing
dishes and doing other chores around the house. Over an hour a day spent on
all these combined is not uncommon. At 1.25x listening speed, I can burn
through an average-sized book in a couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Making time: I find that I have some free time almost every evening to
relax; it's usually not much, maybe 30-45 minutes. Rather than watching TV
or browsing social media, I read. I also spend some of my working
time reading technical books; when I'm really into a technical book, this can
amount to 20-30 minutes a day. Each instance in isolation is not much, but
it really adds up over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the place to mention that I prefer consuming slow media, to the
extent possible. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2022/in-defense-of-books/"&gt;I have a longer blog post&lt;/a&gt;
about this topic alone, but in the context of reading &lt;em&gt;slow media&lt;/em&gt; means I
prefer books to articles, magazines and blog posts. These, in turn, I prefer
over social media. Therefore, given that I spend some small chunk of my day
reading - meaning scanning text with my eyes - I strongly prefer this time to
be spent on books rather than any other text organization format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Reading with my kids: this one is fairly new, from the last year or so. As
my kids grow older, I find that I can read books together with them that both
of us actually enjoy. There are a couple of instances of that in the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2019/summary-of-reading-october-december-2019/"&gt;most recent reading summary&lt;/a&gt;.
This is just like audiobooks in a way - it allows me to &amp;quot;steal&amp;quot; reading time
while doing something else. Reading together with my kids is a lot of fun,
and it combines an activity that's dear to my heart (spending quality time
with them) with another activity - reading. I actually find that some &amp;quot;young
reader&amp;quot; versions of books are better than adult books! They convey very
similar amounts of information in a shorter, clearer way, without spending
text on useless embellishments and trying to pad to 300 pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; Do you read paper books? Audiobooks? Ebooks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Short answer: yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For audiobooks, see the answer above. The rest is split between ebooks and paper
books. My heuristic here is pretty clear: I prefer an ebook, unless it's a book
that has graphics (like images, photos or charts), equations or code in it. I
read ebooks on a Kindle, and I don't like how Kindles do images, equations or
code. But I do prefer them for pure-text books, because a Kindle is lighter,
easier to hold with one hand, and easier to put down (in the sense that it's
easier to find where you left off).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; Do you speed-read?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; No. I experimented a little bit with speed-reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/10/02/speed-reading"&gt;many years ago&lt;/a&gt;, but never really
warmed up to it. I did manage to bring my WPM much higher, but comprehension
suffered, and I also found I enjoy reading less. Lately, the vast majority of
my reading is non-fiction, which makes speed-reading even more challenging,
because comprehension is crucial. I'd say I read physical books at a pretty
average pace now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for audiobooks, I set them to 1.25x because the original speed is unbearably
slow, but this is not fast by any means. Most folks I know listen at 1.25x
at least, and some listen at much faster - like 1.5x or 2x. I found these higher
speeds harder to concentrate with, and comprehension suffers greatly. So I
settled for a more moderate pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; Do you re-read books?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Absolutely. I also group them separately in my reading summaries, so it's
easy to see which books are re-reads. I estimate that about 10-15% of the books
I've been reading recently fall into this category. I've read many books twice,
and some books three or more times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reading good books is very important for me. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/05/15/quality-reading-instead-of-quantity-reading"&gt;A while ago&lt;/a&gt;
I made a resolution to read more for quality than quantity, but this is easier
said then done. Yes, most of my reading is non-fiction, and I spend quite a bit
of time vetting books &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; I read them. But the most effective way to keep
average quality up is to re-read books I found great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How often does it happen that I re-read a book and find almost nothing new in
it? Almost never. Keep in mind that some books are a distillation of many years
of an author's diligent research and writing work; it's very unlikely to &amp;quot;get&amp;quot;
all of it in just a few hours. Reading a book and letting the material simmer in
the back of your mind for some period (a year or more, typically), and then
re-reading is a very effective way to extract more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; Do you always finish a book before starting the next one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; I always have more than one book in progress - one on audio and another
in text. But usually it's even more than one. For example, there is a technical
book I'm slowly plowing through only at certain times (when concentration is
easiest), and quite often if I'm reading something &amp;quot;heavy&amp;quot; I'll put it aside for
a while and read a lighter book. I also have at least one book &amp;quot;in progress&amp;quot;
going with my kids at any given time. So the average is probably around 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is also sometimes asked in the sense of &amp;quot;do you finish all the
books you begin&amp;quot;. Well, not always, but almost. I try to vet books &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt;
carefully before reading them, so I don't get duds often. But every once in a
while I do, and then I have no issue abandoning a particularly bad book in the
middle.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading on a Kindle vs. a paper book</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2012/04/26/reading-on-a-kindle-vs-a-paper-book" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-04-26T05:23:27-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2012-04-26:/2012/04/26/reading-on-a-kindle-vs-a-paper-book</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: &amp;quot;Kindle&amp;quot; here can be probably replaced with any good electronic book reader. I only happen to own a Kindle, so my personal opinion is confined to it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some thoughts on the relative merits of &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; paper books and books read on a Kindle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why a Kindle is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: &amp;quot;Kindle&amp;quot; here can be probably replaced with any good electronic book reader. I only happen to own a Kindle, so my personal opinion is confined to it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some thoughts on the relative merits of &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; paper books and books read on a Kindle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why a Kindle is better (in no particular order):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smaller, slimmer and lighter than most books, while still being big enough to provide a good holding and reading experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Much easier to put down and come back to the correct spot later. Not only you don't need a physical marker, but the pages themselves are significantly smaller so it's easy to stop at the first paragraph and know this is where you should resume reading. I appreciate this a lot when reading while watching my daughter, which means I should put the book down each minute or two and come back to it later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier and cleaner to highlight interesting sections and get back to them later - no need to keep a pen around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A blessing when reading several books simultaneously (which is frequently the case for me). This becomes quite important when traveling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practically every book from Amazon available for you 15 seconds after you decide you want to read it (and you can read a sample before paying).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has a built-in clock.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has built-in dictionaries and you can install more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjustable font size is a blessing for people with poor eyesight (although this is thankfully not my problem yet, I can see how important this is).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why a paper book is better:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its battery lasts longer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration quality is higher, especially in non-fiction books where this is important, and where high-quality color illustrations may be crucial. I think this is temporary, though - it's hard to believe it will still be an issue 5 years from now when e-readers have better screens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More reliable. In normal day-to-day conditions this isn't a big issue, though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Costs much less so you don't worry too much about it getting damaged, lost or stolen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has the good-old feeling and smell of paper. I must admit, however, that when I read on a Kindle, I miss this feeling much less than initially imagined.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gives you the opportunity to fill shelves with books, which is a terrific adornment for every home, especially the &amp;quot;office room&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry><entry><title>"Reading" audiobooks - a first experience</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/09/24/reading-audiobooks-a-first-experience" rel="alternate"></link><published>2007-09-24T19:30:41-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2007-09-24:/2007/09/24/reading-audiobooks-a-first-experience</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;h4&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;
I've just finished "reading" my first audio book. The decision came after I noticed that on the bus back home from work I very rarely can concentrate on reading a paper book, because I'm either tired, being disturbed by people talking around me or both. Besides, now with the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;h4&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;
I've just finished "reading" my first audio book. The decision came after I noticed that on the bus back home from work I very rarely can concentrate on reading a paper book, because I'm either tired, being disturbed by people talking around me or both. Besides, now with the winter on our doorstep, the dusk arrives earlier each day, which makes reading without ruining the eyes hard.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Anyway, to give it a first shot, I browsed to &lt;a href="http://librivox.org/"&gt;LibriVox&lt;/a&gt; to grab myself a free audiobook. LibriVox is somewhat similar to &lt;a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/wiki/Main_Page"&gt;Project Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt;, collecting books with an expired copyright (in the U.S.). However, since getting access to the text of books is considerably easier than recording them on audio, LibriVox has so far collected a little less than a thousand books, while Gutenberg holds tens of thousands.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I must say that the collection on LibriVox isn't large. Clearly, recording a book is a long and difficult task, so it isn't simple to find volunteers. Eventually, I picked up &lt;a href="http://librivox.org/the-adventures-of-sherlock-holmes/"&gt;"The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes"&lt;/a&gt; for an easy start (I'll post a review of the book itself soon, so I won't dwell on its contents here).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The quality of recording&lt;/h4&gt;

LibriVox is operated entirely by volunteers, and often a single book is being recorded by multiple people. In the book I read, the 12 chapters were all narrated by different people. Naturally, the quality varies. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I don't mean the digital quality here - LibriVox allows to download MP3s encoded in 64kbps and 128kbps - and I found the 64kbps perfectly acceptable. What I really want to talk about is the quality of the narrator. In "The Adventures", I had a bad start, as the first reader was quite bad. He had a strange accent, over-dramatized many episodes and generally was difficult to understand. Luckily, all the rest were quite good, and generally I can say it was all very easy to listen to. A couple of the readers were splendid - I couldn't expect a better quality from a purchased audiobook.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

LibriVox's policy is not to allow ratings of chapter quality by users. I can understand their point of view in saying that bad ratings might discourage readers that aren't simple to find anyhow. Nevertheless, I think that allowing ratings would still be better. It would surely encourage readers to do a better job.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

All in all I can't complain, however. As I said, the overall quality of the recordings was very good and the listening experience was enjoyable - I'm pretty sure I didn't lose track of the events because of recording quality even a single time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Speed and concentration&lt;/h4&gt;

The narrators read at a very comfortable speed - like the speed of two people at ease speaking with each other. The total duration of the recording is 10 hours for this book. I checked its length in an electronic text version - and it consists of about 100,000 words, which would take me 5.5 hours to read at my average rate of 300 wpm for books of this kind. So, on one hand, audiobooks are twice "slower". 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

However, there is a very significant factor I'm ignoring here. Reading a book at a sustained rate of 300 wpm isn't an easy task - because you need to stay very focused the whole time. This isn't easy for long stretches of time even in a quiet environment, not to mention a dark, noisy bus when you're tired after a day of work. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

So I think that while I would still prefer reading with my eyes while sitting at ease on my couch at home, listening to audiobooks on the bus or train is a pretty good option even speed-wise, because their rate is constant, and it is much simpler to stay concentrated listening than reading in a noisy environment.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

While on the topic of concentration, it is interesting to notice that although it is easier to keep focus while listening, when you lose it you can completely miss portions of the text. While reading a normal book, I often find that my thoughts have wondered and that I have only a vague clue of what the last page or so was about. However, not all the meaning is lost and after a quick skim I'm back on track. With an audiobook this is different. When my mind wondered for 20 seconds - I found that I &lt;i&gt;completely&lt;/i&gt; missed that part of the recording, as if I didn't hear it at all - and I have to come back to listen to it fully if I deem it important.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Another interesting, and more important point to note is that listening to an audiobook doesn't detriment much my attention to the real world. I even drove while listening for a short time and found no problem concentrating on the road, and understanding the book at the same time. This is probably not surprising, considering that radio talk-shows are a favorite with long-haul drivers of buses and trucks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

To summarize, I had a very positive experience listening to this audiobook. I find that such type of reading fills a niche in times when I find it hard to concentrate but still prefer reading to sitting idly. The speed, while inferior to eye-reading under optimal conditions, is quite comparable on average. And on some occasions, like when taking a walk or driving - audiobooks are a pure win - because you just can't read in any other way.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

What's very important, however - is the quality of the narration. It can make all the change in the world - a bad narrator can make the listening experience irritating and practically useless, so I suppose that buying audiobooks can be a good option as their quality is probably very good and they're not too expensive.
&lt;/p&gt;


    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry><entry><title>quality reading instead of quantity reading</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/05/15/quality-reading-instead-of-quantity-reading" rel="alternate"></link><published>2007-05-15T17:32:07-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T13:41:52-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2007-05-15:/2007/05/15/quality-reading-instead-of-quantity-reading</id><summary type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
        Lately I have a bad feeling about my reading patterns. It seems that when I read, I focus on quantity rather than quality. The bad feeling was especially acute during the vacation, when I was &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/03/15/books-read-during-the-vacation/"&gt;devouring books&lt;/a&gt; at a rate of two per week. 
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I really think I should shift …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
        Lately I have a bad feeling about my reading patterns. It seems that when I read, I focus on quantity rather than quality. The bad feeling was especially acute during the vacation, when I was &lt;a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/03/15/books-read-during-the-vacation/"&gt;devouring books&lt;/a&gt; at a rate of two per week. 
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I really think I should shift my focus to quality reading. I don't just want to read a lots of books, I want to read good books, and I want to read them thoroughly. What bothers me most about quantity reading is that sometimes I don't remember what the book was all about even a short time after finishing it. Why to read at all, then ? My goal in reading is not just passing time - I actually want to learn from the books I read. This is also the reason for the fact that most of the books I read are non-fiction.
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

So, I've decided to implement the following steps in an attempt to bring my reading patterns closer to my goals. In no particular order:
    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When I read a book, I will read it more carefully. This means not just running forward, but trying to understand what I read, cross-referencing with other books and online resources when needed. There is no goal to finish as many books as possible. No rush.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I will write much more detailed book reviews on the books I finish. In part, this will serve as a kind of an exam which will force me to actually read books more thoroughly. In each review I will include:
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A general description of what the book is about, possibly "digesting" the table of contents.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A list of things I learned from the book and I deem important.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A list of things I liked about the book, and a list of things I didn't like.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;My reviews are meant much more for myself than for readers of this blog. Hence, I will not shun from presenting them in a more informative, even if dry, manner, rather than a talkative one.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I will reread some of my favorite books - and possibly will update the reviews for them in the aforementioned manner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is it, for now. I wish myself good luck in this endeavor.
&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry><entry><title>Books read during the vacation</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/03/15/books-read-during-the-vacation" rel="alternate"></link><published>2007-03-15T20:22:15-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2007-03-15:/2007/03/15/books-read-during-the-vacation</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
During the vacation I've read quite a lot of books, at almost twice my normal
rate. There's just more free time on a vacation (and the nightlife in New
Zealand isn't too great ;-))
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Anyway, here is the list of the books I read, in very rough chronological order
(a couple …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
During the vacation I've read quite a lot of books, at almost twice my normal
rate. There's just more free time on a vacation (and the nightlife in New
Zealand isn't too great ;-))
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Anyway, here is the list of the books I read, in very rough chronological order
(a couple of them were finished in 2006, but I'll attribute them to 2007
anyway). I won't be writing the usual full fledged reviews because there's too
many of them, but I do include a short description.
      &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Gideon's spies" by Gordon Thomas &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Telling some of the known facts about Mossad's (Israeli equivalent of CIA or MI6) operations, including many interviews with some of Mossad's past agents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Being Here, Shaping a preferred future" by Christine Loh&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; She is a member of Hong Kong's government and past activist and committee member. Tells about Hong Kong's politics, somewhat autobiographic in nature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Baghdad without a map" by Tony Horwitz&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; The traveling reporter's adventures in the Middle East in the late 80s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Spy catcher" by Peter Wright&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; The former assistant director of MI5 tells about his years in the agency. I heard it was quite a controversial book at its time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Adventure Capitalist" by Jim Rogers&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This rich dude packed himself and his young wife into a special built Mercedes and has done a mighty road trip across the world (152,000 miles), telling about his impressions of the countries' economies along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The journey of man - A genetic odyssey" by Spencer Wells&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Trying to follow the early history of man's journey from Africa colonizing other parts of the world. Interesting but doesn't add much information over other books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"A history of the middle east" by Peter Mansfield&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A careful and expansive account of the history of the Middle East from early times to the second half of the 20th century.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"From Beirut to Jerusalem" by Thomas Friedman&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;He was a reporter in Lebanon for a few years, and then moved to Israel. This book is his story of the turbulent events in the history of these countries. This is one of the better books I've read on the middle east.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The Time Traveler's Wife" by Audrey Niffenegger&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An unusual science fiction - like story of man who keeps jumping in time and his wife. Very readable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"World war 1939-1945" by Peter Young&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A brief but detailed history of WWII, told by a Brittish brigadier turned historian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The bride stripped bare" by Anonymous&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A confession of an adulterous, sex-addicted woman in London. I found it bizarre and couldn't wait to finish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Following the equator" by Mark Twain&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A humorous travel log in various countries of the British Commonwealth in the beginning of the 20th century. Entertaining, but its age shows well as some stories deal with completely unfamiliar events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Electric Universe" by David Bodanis&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A brief history of electricity and its major applications. Although this book definitely lacks in depth, it is very well written and fun to read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Longtitude" by Dava Sobel&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A small book telling the story of how an English engineer devised a clock accurate enough to measure longitude and solved the great problem of marine navigation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The six day war" by Randolph S. and Winston S. Churchill&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A small book telling the story of the Israeli-Arab war in 1967.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The prince and the pauper" by Mark Twain&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A short entertaining fairy tale about a prince and a pauper in London who switched places. More a children's book than anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Terra incognita" by Sara Wheeler&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This lady spent a few months in Antarctica, harassing people on various research bases on the continent. Pretty good account of what it's like down there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Once while traveling" by Tony and Maureen Wheeler&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An autobiographic account of the couple who created the Lonely Planet publication. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Exodus" by Leon Uris&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fiction story of the years leading to the creation of the state of Israel and a few years after that. A very good book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"1421" by Gavin Menzies&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A very curious and well researched account of China's explorations in the 15th century. The author makes some bold claims about Chinese colonization of the Americas and outposts in Australia and New Zealand, and backs them with lots of seemingly solid evidence. Whether what he says is true or not, it's a good, well-written history book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The island of lost maps" by Miles Harvey&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The main theme of this book is following the story of an ancient-map thief who stole precious maps from libraries and universities. On the way the author tells a little about the world of cartography and engages on a quest of self-discovery. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"One L" by Scott Turow&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An account of the first year in the prestigious Harvard Law School. The book is well written and is an interesting insight into the world of elite education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Questioning the Millennium" by Stephen J. Gould&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A mini-book in which Gould tries to explain the true meaning of the year 2000 in Christianity, exploring its roots and discusses when it is really appropriate to celebrate. A cute, quick, not too deep read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Why in the world" by John Demko&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Displays the topic of geography, emphasizing on what geographers do and how knowing geography is important. The first half of the book is interesting, but the second is completely useless - a "state of affairs" summary for each country in the world. The book being written in 1992, this is hardly interesting now. Wikipedia is a better source of information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Reading"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Triple your reading speed" by Wade Cutler</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/10/20/book-review-triple-your-reading-speed-by-wade-cutler" rel="alternate"></link><published>2006-10-20T10:44:38-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2006-10-20:/2006/10/20/book-review-triple-your-reading-speed-by-wade-cutler</id><summary type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
        As I mentioned before, I got interested in the topic of speed reading and bought a couple of books on the subject. One of these books is "Triple your reading speed" by Wade Cutler. I finished reading it a couple of weeks ago and waited with the review to self-assess …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
        As I mentioned before, I got interested in the topic of speed reading and bought a couple of books on the subject. One of these books is "Triple your reading speed" by Wade Cutler. I finished reading it a couple of weeks ago and waited with the review to self-assess my progress in speed reading.
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Speed reading is quite difficult to measure. In the initial speed-test in the book I scored 280 wpm for a short article. In subsequent speed tests I reached 350-380 wpm on short articles, and 300 wpm on a whole book ("Animal Farm"). I think that it does represent nice progress (not tripling, of course, but a few 10s of %s of acceleration) since concentrating on a whole book for a few hours is much more difficult than concentrating on a short article for a few minutes.
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I really enjoyed this book since Mr. Cutler presents techniques which are down to earth. Speed reading is one of those topics where you get promised wonders, pay money to achieve it and after a short excitement period find that you haven't gained anything. In this light, a book like "Triple your reading speed", while having a loud name, stands pretty well overall since the techniques in it are practical, believable, and it contains lots of exercises to test your skills. In fact, the "teaching" phase itself in this book is very short - probably less than 50 pages long. The book explains how expanding the peripheral vision is important in order to catch more than one word with a single glimpse, how sub-vocalization (the act of saying the words "in your head" while you read) is harmful and how to stay focused on what your read withoud spending time jumping forward and backwards. The rest of the book is packed with exercises - short articles that take 2 - 15 minutes to read, with their word count and a comprehension test. This way you can not only test the speed but also your comprehension of the text.
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Comprehension is a big topic in speed reading. Skimming is not what I'm trying to achieve - I want to actually read the whole text and understand everything I read. Thus, it's obvious that the reading speed must depend on the difficulty of a text. No speed-reading marketing guru will ever convince me that a normal human being can read a challenging non-fiction book at 1000 wpm understanding everything. It just can't happen - in difficult books I find myself slowed down not by the speed of my eyes seeing all words, but by my brain trying to process the text and understand it. I do recognize that many simpler texts, like most novels, can be read quicker - since there it's the speed of the eyes what limits me.
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I feel I learned from this book and have already improved. But to further improve one needs a lot of practice - which is what I'm doing now. In every book I read, I try to adjust my pace to the material and read as fast as I can understand it. I feel my reading speed has indeed improved, and I hope that with further practice it will improve even more. 
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

So this book is recommended - in the sea of charlatan information, it has some
solid advice and good exercises to get on the improvement path. Don't expect to
really triple your reading speed, though (unless it's really slow, like &lt; 150
wpm), especially while retaining an acceptable comprehension rate.
        &lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry><entry><title>Speed reading</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2006/10/02/speed-reading" rel="alternate"></link><published>2006-10-02T10:44:41-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2006-10-02:/2006/10/02/speed-reading</id><summary type="html">
  &lt;p&gt;
        While I was in the US, a commertial on the TV there got me into thinking - why won't I try to teach myself speed reading. I read quite a lot, and if with some exercise I could increase the speed of my reading without sacrificing comprehension, wouldn't that be great …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
  &lt;p&gt;
        While I was in the US, a commertial on the TV there got me into thinking - why won't I try to teach myself speed reading. I read quite a lot, and if with some exercise I could increase the speed of my reading without sacrificing comprehension, wouldn't that be great ?
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

So I bought a couple of books on the subject and started working through one of them a couple of days ago. In the beginning, they measure your reading speed and comprehension using a sample text. I average on about 290 wpm (words per minute) with 80% comprehension, which isn't bad considering that English is my 3rd language. The average for US university students is somewhere between 250 and 350 wpm.
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The first book I started working with is called "Triple your reading speed". I will write a fuller review when I finish it, but generally it claims that whatever your reading speed is, you can easily triple it without sacrificing comprehension. The book has tons of sample texts with comprehension tests for measurement, and some useful tips on how to get rid of slow reading habits, along with 20 or so pages of eye-exercises that should (in theory) help reading faster.
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I'm not sure how well I'm going yet - it takes more exercise to figure this out. What I noticed is that speed reading is typical pseudo-science. There are a lot of people and companies with wonderous offers out there in the Internet, and a lot of sceptics. BTW, whenever you approach a new subject, it is very important to thoroughly read the sceptics as well as proponents. 
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

I see 2 kinds of speed-reading advertisers: there are people who claim anyone can reach speeds in the thousands of wpm. Well, I find this just impossible to believe, sorry. Such reading is called "skimming" - you don't really read the text, you skim through it intelligently, trying to gather as much as possible in a short time. While this may be beneficial in rare cases (like studying for an exam which is 3 hours away), I don't think it's applicable for "reading for enjoyment". One notable joke about this is "I've just finished reading War in Peace in 2 hours. It's something about Russia".
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The other kind of speed-reaiding proponents pose more logical claims. They say one can comfortable improve reading speed to 500 - 900 wpm with full comprehension, by seriously investing in exercise of eye-training and getting rid of harmful practices. This I can believe, and the exercises in the book (and in online tutorials) are logical enough - I can see how my reading speed can improve by doing them. The exercises focus mainly on developing better peripheral vision, i.e. catching more words around the ones you're focusing your eyes on. Mechanics are inherently slow, and the brain is capable of catching concepts faster than the eyes can move, so this is quite beneficial. Another focus is getting rid of sub-vocalization (the urge to read "silently" hearing every word in your head) and get used to a better focus on the text (not letting your thoughts wander).
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

All in all, I'm still optimistic about this. I don't think I'll get to 1000+
wpm, because my goal in reading is first and foremost understanding and fun, but
I believe I will be able to increase my speed to at least 500 - 600 wpm in
reading novels and lighter material, without sacrificing comprehension. If this
will allow me to get through more books in the same time, why not. I'm still
sceptical about the ability to speed-read more difficult texts, though (and I
mainly read non-fiction). Some concepts just take brain-time to grasp.
  &lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry><entry><title>how I read ebooks on a Palm</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/07/23/how-i-read-ebooks-on-a-palm" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-07-23T10:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-07-23:/2005/07/23/how-i-read-ebooks-on-a-palm</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;I read books on my Palm Tungsten E. It is very convenient - once you get used to it, not much different from a printed book.
&lt;p&gt;The only problem is the multitute of book reader programs / formats / funny quoting styles / languages and so on which often makes preparing an ebook for …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;I read books on my Palm Tungsten E. It is very convenient - once you get used to it, not much different from a printed book.
&lt;p&gt;The only problem is the multitute of book reader programs / formats / funny quoting styles / languages and so on which often makes preparing an ebook for reading quite a challenge. This is when you're thankful that you know Perl...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reader of choice is &lt;a href="http://palmfiction.sourceforge.net/" rel="nofollow"&gt;Palmfiction&lt;/a&gt; - an open source program that understands many formats and languages (I read Russian, English and Spanish with it), has nice fonts and useful indications of the time, location in book and battery power % constantly on the top of the screen. Additionally, once you move your mouse over a word (or tap on it) it's taken right into the clipboard buffer so translating words using a dictionary is a very simple two tap process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The format I prefer to use is zTxt - a compressed text format that Palmfiction understands and that shrinks books to ~1/3 of their plain text size. The free converter &lt;a href="http://www.hpc.ru/soft/software.phtml?id=4511" rel="nofollow"&gt;WinMakezTxt&lt;/a&gt;  (warning, Russian interface) converts .rtf, .txt and .html to .ztxt and packs it into a .pdb so it's right there ready for the Palm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far so good... But many books are still not suitable for this process. PDFs, for instance. I detest the Palm Acrobat Reader - it's slow and bulky, and its converter is even bulkier. It isn't dictionary friendly and the display is uncomfortable. So, I'm converting PDFs to something more convenient. &lt;a href="http://pdftohtml.sourceforge.net/" rel="nofollow"&gt;pdftohtml&lt;/a&gt; is a nice opensource utility that converts PDFs to HTML or XML. Then, I can either convert HTML directly to zTxt with WinMakezTxt or format it to my needs with Perl using HTML::TokeParser::Simple first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, RTFs are readily convertible to zTxt, but today I had to massage a RTF a little with Perl to suit my needs. The RTF file I refer to had dashes for quote delimiters that were for some reason invisible in text / zText formats. A simple script solved my problem here. For future, more challenging transformations, I might use Perl's RTF processing modules.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Hardware &amp; Gadgets"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "How to read a book" by M. Adler, C. Van Doren</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/01/06/book-review-how-to-read-a-book-by-m-adler-c-van-doren" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-01-06T11:41:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-01-06:/2004/01/06/book-review-how-to-read-a-book-by-m-adler-c-van-doren</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
        I spend quite a lot of time reading books. Ergo,
it's not surprising that finding out more about
the act of reading itself interests me. Nevertheless,
I didn't look for this book... it found me, during
one of my random browsing sessions of Amazon.
When I saw the title I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
        I spend quite a lot of time reading books. Ergo,
it's not surprising that finding out more about
the act of reading itself interests me. Nevertheless,
I didn't look for this book... it found me, during
one of my random browsing sessions of Amazon.
When I saw the title I immediately got intrigued - you
don't see much books about books. When I read the
description, editorial's review and a few users'
comments, I immediately felt it's a "must have", and
added it to my wishlist, buying it after a couple
of months.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
With this in mind, my expectations from "How to
read a book" were quite high, on one hand. On the
other hand, what can someone teach me about reading ?
I mean, reading is the basic art of following with
your eyes a few pages (or a few hundred pages), trying
to understand what the author means. Sometimes it's
for entertainment, and sometimes it's for education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Well, it appears that there is something to learn
about reading, but the authors of "How to read" don't
even pretend to teach you about the reading you think
of when you think of "reading".
The authors divide the activity of reading
to four categories: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Elementary - this is the reading
we all think of, mostly for entertainment - read the
book once, cover to cover, put it back on the shelf.
If the book's bad, not much to do. If it's good, in the
worst case you gained a few hours of entertainment, in
the best case you also learned something. The authors
don't talk much about this kind of reading, because
we all know how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Inspectional - you have a book in your hands, and you
should decide whether you want to read it. The book
is 800 pages long, and you have 30 minutes to decide.
What do you do ? This is not a completely fictitious
scenario. Consider taking a stroll through a bookstore,
picking up a book from the shelf and deciding whether
to buy it. Consider going to the library, finding some
book on the topic you need, and deciding whether you
really want to read this book. You are faced with
the challenge of Inspectional reading - inspecting the
book in a limited time. So what do you do ? This,
"How to read a book" tries to teach. (Read front cover,
foreword, back cover, go through the table of contents,
last few pages, last pages of chapters, index, etc...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Analytical - this type of reading the authors develop
the most, devoting a big part of the book to it. This
is reading a serious book, seriously. By serious I mean
not just for entertainment, because there Elementary
reading would suffice. I mean reading a book that it
over your head - in order to learn something new. Here
lays the most important lesson from "How to read a book",
by the way. The authors (rightfully) claim that if you
really want to expand your thinking and "grow your mind",
you should read books that are over your capacity, not
under it. By reading easy books you won't gain much. You
will, however, gain a lot by reading works that are
hard to you, that you find hard to understand. The act
of (analytically - using methods the authors teach
during this chapter) reading this book and understanding
it is some kind of enlightment - you have expanded your
thinking - you can now grasp something you could not
grasp before. It's a very good lesson from this book,
in my opinion. So, Analytical reading is the act of reading
such books - how to understand the important story line, the
author's questions, his problems, solutions to these
problems, understanding where the author comes from,
(dis)agreeing with the author, et cetera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The last type of reading the authors present is Syntopical
reading. This is the reading of several books on the same
subject, trying to gain from them something that's not
in any single book. The subject must be something relatively
vague - something which isn't clearly defined and agreed on
by everyone. Different authors should have a different
opinion on the subject, and by syntopically reading their books,
you can form an opinion of your own, which is possibly not
the opinion of any of the authors you've read. This is discovery
and mind expansion in its purest sense.
Hence, IMHO, is more for the researchers,
as Syntopical reading takes a very long time, but its
benefits are probably formulating some new ideas about
complicated subjects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The book is concluded with a recommended reading list,
of books that are "over most people's heads", and a few
exercises in reading (with questions), which at first
I wanted to skip, but eventually went through them and
enjoyed quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
All in all, I liked this book. It didn't stand to my original
expectation, but could it ? I'm not sure. It taught me other
things, however. The most important lesson I gained is that
one should read hard books, but good ones - for becoming
smarter. I guess I'm on the right way trying to get through
the best classics of the past two centuries (a list I mentioned
before in this journal, which has many similarities with the
recommended reading list of this book). For now, I'm at 17 out
of 110, so there's still a long way to go :-) I hope that "How to
read a book" will help me tackle some of the trickier works
on this list.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry></feed>