<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Eli Bendersky's website - Spanish</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/feeds/spanish.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://eli.thegreenplace.net/</id><updated>2023-02-04T15:35:51-08:00</updated><entry><title>Book review: "Cien años de soledad" by Gabriel García Márquez</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2008/06/09/book-review-cien-anos-de-soledad-by-gabriel-garcia-marquez" rel="alternate"></link><published>2008-06-09T12:59:55-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2008-06-09:/2008/06/09/book-review-cien-anos-de-soledad-by-gabriel-garcia-marquez</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
(read in Spanish)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Yes, I've finished reading "One hundred years of solitude" in Spanish. I began
this endeavor months ago (somewhere in mid 2007 I reckon), and today it was
completed. Why did it take so long ? For a couple of reasons, I guess. First of
all, I read most …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
(read in Spanish)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Yes, I've finished reading "One hundred years of solitude" in Spanish. I began
this endeavor months ago (somewhere in mid 2007 I reckon), and today it was
completed. Why did it take so long ? For a couple of reasons, I guess. First of
all, I read most of it with a dictionary in hand, which made the pace
excruciatingly slow (10 pages per hour or so). Second, the book is far from
having a fluid plot that's easy to follow, so consuming it in large quantities
can be very difficult.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Anyway, now that it's done, I'm proud of having finished it. I read the book
before (6-7 years ago), in English. Even though my English was pretty good back
then, the book was very difficult, as it used a lot of high language. I recall
wondering how reading such a book in its native Spanish would feel - perhaps
this is what triggered my desire to learn Spanish, though I'm not certain about
this. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

CAS (acronym of the Spanish name), as it is frequently referred to, is
considered one of the most notable works of Latin literature, widely acclaimed
as second only to Don Quixote. Márquez received the Nobel prize in literature
for his works, of which CAS is the principal. It tells the story of the Buendía
family, set in the 19th and 20th centuries in the small village Macondo (which
was founded by the head of the family) in Colombia. The story deals with seven
generations of the Buendías, most of which have the same name, which is a
frequent criticism of the novel. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Naming all the family males either Aureliano or José Arcadio (or some variation
thereof) is a deliberate trick by Márquez, to drill in the main theme of the
book - which is the repetitiveness of time and history. Needless to say, it gets
quite confusing at times, and if your book doesn't have a helpful family tree
depicted in the beginning, consult an online resource. Otherwise, it's too easy
to get lost (unless you're reading the whole book in a single sitting - but I
wonder who could do that...)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Another recurring theme in the book is surrealism. Insomnia that hit a whole
town for weeks, rain that lasts years, yellow butterflies, increased fecundity
of farm animals, colored ants and small fish made of gold are only some of the
"wacky" fantasies CAS is full of. These too, are part of the theme of eternal
recurrence of patterns in the lives of the Buendías.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

And it's impossible to write a review of this book without mentioning solitude
and loneliness, that are perhaps the main feeling and state the author tries to
transmit to his readers. How you'll understand it depends on you, and I believe
that everyone can see something for himself in this theme.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Finally, I want to provide two quotes from the book I liked and that describe
the book well. They're in Spanish, and I don't have enough literary pizzazz to
translate them to English in a convincing way.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

From the conversation of Aureliano Babilonia with Pillar Ternera close to the end:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
No había ningún misterio en el corazón de un Buendía que fuera impenetrable para
ella, porque un siglo de naipes y de experiencias le había enseñado que la
historia de la familia era un engranaje de repeticiones irreparables, una rueda
giratoria que hubiera seguido dando vueltas hasta la eternidad, de no haber sido
por el desgaste progresivo e irremediable del eje.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

And the last sentence in the book:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Sin embargo, antes de llegar al verso final, ya había comprendido que no saldría
jamás de ese cuarto, pues estaba previsto que la ciudad de los espejos (o
espejismos) sería arrasada por el viento y desterrada de la memoria de los
hombres, en el instante en que Aureliano Babilonia acabara de decifrar los
pergaminos, y que todo lo escrito en ellos era irrepetible desde siempre y para
siempre, porque los estirpes condenados a cien años de soledad no tenían una
segunda oportunidad sobre la tierra.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I'm asking myself if I like the book. I don't have the answer. There are things
about it I really dislike, and some things I like beyond my own understanding.
After reading it once, I took it up again, and can't be sure that I won't read
it once again sometime in the future. It's still a mystery for me.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Countdown to Spanish" by Gail Stein</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/07/20/book-review-countdown-to-spanish-by-gail-stein" rel="alternate"></link><published>2007-07-20T12:37:14-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2007-07-20:/2007/07/20/book-review-countdown-to-spanish-by-gail-stein</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
The secondary title of the book is "Learn to communicate in 24 hours".
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

A couple of years ago I got this book in electronic form and browsed through it
for some time. I had the impression it is pretty good so I decided to purchase a
paper copy and study …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;
The secondary title of the book is "Learn to communicate in 24 hours".
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

A couple of years ago I got this book in electronic form and browsed through it
for some time. I had the impression it is pretty good so I decided to purchase a
paper copy and study through it. Unfortunately, my initial judgment has failed
me in this case. This book isn't too good. It's quite bad, really. "With
&lt;i&gt;Countdown to Spanish&lt;/i&gt;, in just 24 hours your can learn to speak like a
native in all sorts of everyday situations" - says the back cover. Yeah right !!
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The first part of this book presents the Spanish language for general use,
discussing basic vocabulary and grammar. It is the better part of the book,
although I don't like the way of presentation used by the author. Instead of
showing many examples, she just bombards the reader with grammar rules,
discussing pretty complex rules early on. For example, the 5th chapter (1/5 of
the way through the book) teaches the Future Perfect and Perfect Conditional
tenses - some of the more complex tenses of the language, and that after only a
minimal teaching of the simpler topics ! 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The second part of the book is the really bad one, however. It's a simple
categorized dictionary, plumped into the book to bring it to 24 chapters. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

What I would expect from a good book that tries to teach you some skill is a
thorough set of exercises. There are exercises in this book, but they're a joke.
After a long chapter explaining many concepts, the author provides 5-6 trivial
questions, usually only on 1/4th of the material taught by the chapter. This is
no way to teach.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The book has some nice spots here and there (the chapters on Pronunciation and
Asking Questions come to mind), but all in all it's very unhelpful - you can
spend your time and money better on other books. 
&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>Typing Spanish characters on a standard keyboard</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2007/05/10/typing-spanish-characters-on-a-standard-keyboard" rel="alternate"></link><published>2007-05-10T19:53:10-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2007-05-10:/2007/05/10/typing-spanish-characters-on-a-standard-keyboard</id><summary type="html">
        Spanish has some characters that are not in the English alphabet. It is possible to type them on Windows using Alt + numeric keypad codes. For example, typing 0241 on the numeric keypad while holding the Alt key will produce ñ.

Here is a list of special Spanish characters:

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Á - 0193 …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        Spanish has some characters that are not in the English alphabet. It is possible to type them on Windows using Alt + numeric keypad codes. For example, typing 0241 on the numeric keypad while holding the Alt key will produce ñ.

Here is a list of special Spanish characters:

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Á - 0193&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;á - 0225&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;É - 0201&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;é - 0233&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Í - 0205&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;í - 0237&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ó - 0211&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ó - 0243&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ú - 0218&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ú - 0250&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ñ - 0209&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ñ - 0241&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ü - 0252&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;¡ - 0161 (inverted exclamation mark)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;¿ - 0191 (inverted question mark)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

¡Sé que esto va a ser muy útil para mí!
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Los caminos de Mitan" by Luis G Prado</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/07/22/book-review-los-caminos-de-mitan-by-luis-g-prado" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-07-22T11:34:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-07-22:/2005/07/22/book-review-los-caminos-de-mitan-by-luis-g-prado</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;I downloaded this free ebook in order to read it on my Palm. It's very small (a few dozen pages, hard to tell when reading from a Palm) and I finished it in a few days. I remember the first book I read in Spanish - was it hard ! It took …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;I downloaded this free ebook in order to read it on my Palm. It's very small (a few dozen pages, hard to tell when reading from a Palm) and I finished it in a few days. I remember the first book I read in Spanish - was it hard ! It took me a lot of time and I barely understood what I read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now the situation is far better, a small book takes only a few days, I understand most of what I read and use the dictionary for words I don't understand out of context (which isn't many, perhaps 2 words per 3 sentences on average).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, this is a nice small book from the fantasy genre. The story is of a group of powerful warriors in some imaginary world, who are summoned upon by their king to serve him in a war. However, as they find out, someone else took over the throne and wants them for a completely different reason. I won't go into spoilers, but it truly is a very short book with not much content - a short story, really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now on to something muchlonger...&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Yo Robot" by Isaac Asimov</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/07/12/book-review-yo-robot-by-isaac-asimov" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-07-12T21:16:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-07-12:/2005/07/12/book-review-yo-robot-by-isaac-asimov</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Second read of this book for me, this time in Spanish...
&lt;p&gt;
Yo (I) Robot is Asimov's prelude to the great Robot series - a collection of short stories that shed some light on the initial development of the positronic-brain robots, the people envolved in their design and testing, and the issues …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Second read of this book for me, this time in Spanish...
&lt;p&gt;
Yo (I) Robot is Asimov's prelude to the great Robot series - a collection of short stories that shed some light on the initial development of the positronic-brain robots, the people envolved in their design and testing, and the issues arising from interacting with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For some reason, I didn't enjoy it this time as much as I did the first time I read it. Maybe it's because it wasn't new, maybe because I have higher demands now ? "I Robot" mainly represents the problems with the "three robotic laws" and the hideous loopholes arising from their cross-interaction. The robotic laws are an example of a "bad spec" - unclear, ambiguous, too fuzzy, inconsistent. But hey, probably the "spec" of our brains is not much better :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, Asimov's Foundation and Robots series are highly recommended and this book serves as an important introduction, so it's a must read for anyone serious to get into Asimov.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Fundacion" by Isaac Asimov</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/06/03/book-review-fundacion-by-isaac-asimov" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-06-03T11:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-06-03:/2005/06/03/book-review-fundacion-by-isaac-asimov</id><summary type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Yes, you've read it right - Fundacion, not Foundation. The reason for that is simple - "fundacion" es el traduccion de "foundation" a Espanol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Proceeding with my Spanish-reading, I took onto something familiar. I've read all of Asimov's Foundation and Robots books a few years ago and liked them a lot. So …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Yes, you've read it right - Fundacion, not Foundation. The reason for that is simple - "fundacion" es el traduccion de "foundation" a Espanol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Proceeding with my Spanish-reading, I took onto something familiar. I've read all of Asimov's Foundation and Robots books a few years ago and liked them a lot. So, I decided, a re-read could be fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And it was fun indeed ! Creo que estoy avanzando mucho en mi entendimiento de Espanol. Uso el diccionario raramente y puedo entender la mayoria de las frases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had this feeling when I first read Foundation, and I have it now too - although the book was written a few decades ago, it doesn't seem too anachronistic. The "future" it describes sounds reasonable by all standards, I think. This may have been done deliberately by Asimov - by not focusing on technology he makes it look believeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The one focus Asimov does make is on atomic energy. As we know, atomic reactors indeed give almost unlimited amounts of energy, but at a high cost - pollution, fear of meltdown, etc. But fusion energy promises to solve this, as soon as scientists find how to tame it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's one thing that sounds sad in Asimov's future though - it's that there are no aliens... Are we really alone in this huge galaxy ? I don't think so...&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Harry Potter y la piedra filosofal"</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2005/01/14/book-review-harry-potter-y-la-piedra-filosofal" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-01-14T20:14:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T15:35:51-08:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2005-01-14:/2005/01/14/book-review-harry-potter-y-la-piedra-filosofal</id><summary type="html">
        by J.K. Rolling
&lt;p&gt;
Yay, my first serious book in Spanish. Not the first overall, because I read a
smallish (25 pages) book for beginners, but certainly the first /real/
one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I admit, I've never read Harry Potter before. I know some consider this as falling behind, but my excuse …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        by J.K. Rolling
&lt;p&gt;
Yay, my first serious book in Spanish. Not the first overall, because I read a
smallish (25 pages) book for beginners, but certainly the first /real/
one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I admit, I've never read Harry Potter before. I know some consider this as falling behind, but my excuse is that I waited to read it in Spanish. And, now having read it, I think I made a good choice. Harry Potter is a great book to learn Spanish from - it's easy going, interesting, and the language is not too high. I came to a point where I understand what I read without a dictionary, except for a few sporadic words per page that don't ruin the comprehension. I feel I'm now much stronger in Spanish than before I started reading it.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
As for the book itself - it's certainly entertaining. I wouldn't rate it anywhere near my "best books" list, and those who have the nerve to even mention a comparison to LOTR are delirious, but this book has its merits, and its popularity can be understood. The writing of JK Rowling is fast paced and flowing, funny and easy to follow.
The level of the language is higher than I expected, which is good because the book is so popular with children - it lets them improve their vocabulary a little.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I think it's needless to mention that I found it to be quite childish, though given the audience, that can be understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, I plan to buy the 2nd Harry Potter book as well - to keep practicing my Spanish. I wouldn't waste my reading time on Harry Potter if I wouldn't be able to find it in Spanish. As a book for language learning, it's great (my friend perfects his French by reading and rereading its translation).&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Spanish with Michel Thomas" by Michel Thomas</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/11/11/book-review-spanish-with-michel-thomas-by-michel-thomas" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-11-11T21:34:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-11-11:/2004/11/11/book-review-spanish-with-michel-thomas-by-michel-thomas</id><summary type="html">
        (This is an audio book)&lt;p&gt;
"Spanish with Michel Thomas" is a beginner-level audio course, about 8-9 hours long (8 CDs - conveniently lumped into a single disk of MP3). Since I'm quite above the beginner level, my main aim in picking it up was to learn and practice pronounciation. It's difficult …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
        (This is an audio book)&lt;p&gt;
"Spanish with Michel Thomas" is a beginner-level audio course, about 8-9 hours long (8 CDs - conveniently lumped into a single disk of MP3). Since I'm quite above the beginner level, my main aim in picking it up was to learn and practice pronounciation. It's difficult to learn a language entirely from printed books - you also need to hear people speaking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This audio course has a curious structure. The narrator speaks with two students (the listener is the third) - presenting new words and concepts to them and asking them to construct sentences. The listener is encouraged to construct his sentences while the students think them over, and then compare the results with the students and the narrator.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
All in all, the experience of hearing this audio book is very nice. Here are some specific points I noticed:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the narrator says in the beginning, one really doesn't need any memorizing or homework to study with this course. Somehow, it gets into your head.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pace is not linear. The lectures start steeply, introducing many new words and concepts. Somewhere towards the middle it literally dies and I found myself just scrolling through whole lessons where Michel Thomas was repeating the same material (probably for beginners...). Towards the end the pace accelerates again. In the last 15 lessons, more material is taught than in the preceding 50.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lessons only marginally touch the past tenses in the last lessons. It's pity that words like fue (was) were not taught.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjectives also got almost no attention during the course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The concept of two other students is nice, but with a catch - the girl student is quite good, but the guy is awful. You'll be biting your elbows waiting for him to pronounce basic stuff, even after it's been repeated lots of times. Sometimes it's just too annoying ! The only use for this, as I see it, is make the listener confident that he's good - at least better than the poor chap who can't even pronounce the "ar" ending correctly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

This audio book is really a very nice way to learn Spanish, although as I noticed it's quite basic. However, it does teach pronounciation - just what I wanted. I can't say I didn't pick a few useful words / rules from it - so overall I'm quite happy. For beginners, I think it's an excellent choice.&lt;p&gt;
Entonces, si quieres estudiar espanol, compre este libro pronto !&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>tech blogs in Spanish</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2004/10/05/tech-blogs-in-spanish" rel="alternate"></link><published>2004-10-05T10:13:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2004-10-05:/2004/10/05/tech-blogs-in-spanish</id><content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;I've added a tech-blog in Spanish to my aggregator - &lt;a href="http://barrapunto.com/" rel="nofollow"&gt;Barrapunto&lt;/a&gt;. It's Slashdot like, a community blog.
&lt;p&gt;
Anyone knows other nice tech-blogs in Spanish ?&lt;/p&gt;

    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry><entry><title>Book review: "Lola" by Loreto de Miguel and Alba Santos</title><link href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2003/10/01/book-review-lola-by-loreto-de-miguel-and-alba-santos" rel="alternate"></link><published>2003-10-01T10:29:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:08:24-07:00</updated><author><name>Eli Bendersky</name></author><id>tag:eli.thegreenplace.net,2003-10-01:/2003/10/01/book-review-lola-by-loreto-de-miguel-and-alba-santos</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;Mi primer libro en espa&amp;#241;ol !!!!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

That's right, the first book I've read in Spanish. Though calling it a book is
an overstatement, and it might not fit very well into my latest rush for the
classics, this 23 page detective story (level 3 out of 5 for Spanish learners)
is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;Mi primer libro en espa&amp;#241;ol !!!!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

That's right, the first book I've read in Spanish. Though calling it a book is
an overstatement, and it might not fit very well into my latest rush for the
classics, this 23 page detective story (level 3 out of 5 for Spanish learners)
is nevertheless first, and I sincerely hope many more will follow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The book is part of a series about a private detector - Pepe Rey. In this story,
he meets his girlfriend-from-youth Lola in Barcelona, but she evades him for
some weird reasons. In the end (hey, that's only about 20 pages later !) he
finds out she heads a group of jewelry robbers, and has escaped to Brazil. Not
very deep, indeed. The important thing, of course, is that the book is
completely in Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

It took me forever to read it... Half of the words I didn't understand and
heavily used the dictionary. When I was wholly into it, my rate was half an hour
for a page... slow but fruitful. I think it made my grasp of some Spanish more
solid, though I didn't learn *a lot*. More important, I saw that I can
understand the general goings even without a dictionary (though this is a very
vague understanding), which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

So, my plans for future reading "en Espa&amp;#241;ol" are to tackle "Aventuras de
Gordon Pym" by E.A.Poe I bought in Spain. It is a normal book (300 pages) and
will probably take a year to read :-), but hey I'm in no hurry.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="Book reviews"></category><category term="Spanish"></category></entry></feed>